<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Death a deliverance, or, A funeral discourse, preach'd (in part) on the decease of Mrs. Mary Doolittle, (late wife of Mr. Thomas Doolittle, minister of the Gospel in London) who departed this life the 16th of Decemb. 1692 by John Shower.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60128</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184223</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13111291</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13111291</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60128)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 779:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Death a deliverance, or, A funeral discourse, preach'd (in part) on the decease of Mrs. Mary Doolittle, (late wife of Mr. Thomas Doolittle, minister of the Gospel in London) who departed this life the 16th of Decemb. 1692 by John Shower.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 127, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Abr. Chandler ... and Samuel Wade ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication dated Febr. 13, 1692/3.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Doolittle, Mary, d. 1692.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, V, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97664:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97664:1"/>
            <p>Death a Deliverance. OR, A Funeral Diſcourſe, Preach'd (in Part) on the Deceaſe of M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>MARY DOOLITTLE,</hi> (Late WIFE of Mr. <hi>THOMAS DOOLITTLE,</hi> Miniſter of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>) Who Departed this LIFE the 16th of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1692.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN SHOWER.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 7.1.</hi>
               </bibl> The Day of Death is better, than the day of one's Birth.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abr. Chandler,</hi> at the <hi>Chyrurgeons-Arms,</hi> at the Entrance into <hi>Bartholomews-Cloſe,</hi> in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet.</hi> And <hi>Samuel Wade,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> under the <hi>Piaza</hi> of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill. 1693.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97664:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97664:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS Reverend and Honoured Friend, and Brother, Mr. <hi>DOOLITTLE.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF you did not know how little time I have to command, I ſhould need an Excuſe for not having ſooner finiſht the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription,
<pb facs="tcp:97664:3"/>and Enlargment of the following Diſcourſe: which was preached at your Deſire, on the Death of your Wife, and now on the ſame Motive is made publick. If it may any way Contribute to allay your Sorrow for your great Loſs, or be uſeful to any Others, eſpecially the Relations and Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Deceaſed, I ſhall not Repent it.</p>
            <p>The Text recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me is every way ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:97664:3"/>to the Occaſion, and to your Deſign of my inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Living from it, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever defective the Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Performance be. You will not expect (from me, at leaſt you cannot,) that a Subject ſo often treated on by Others, ſhould be beautified with new noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Neither do I fear to have diſpleaſed you, by the citation of ſome Paſſages, out of the practical Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Excellent <hi>Mr. Baxter.</hi> For whoſe Memory
<pb facs="tcp:97664:4"/>
               <hi>I</hi> know, you have ſo dear a Value; and by whom, while he Lived, you had the Honour, and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to be eſteemed and loved. For my own part, <hi>I</hi> think my ſelf obliged to take all Occaſions, to expreſs my Thankfulneſs to God for the Miniſtry and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, the Books, and Counſels of that Great and Holy Man: whom <hi>I</hi> reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to have been a Publick Bleſſing to the Nation, and the Age: and am confident
<pb facs="tcp:97664:4"/>that more Impartial Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will acknowledg it. <hi>I</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doubt but that you, with many thouſand Others, do Joyn with me, in Praiſing God for his long Life. That One ſo often near the Grave, and ſo fit for the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per better World, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in ſuch delightful Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughts of <hi>Everlaſting Reſt,</hi> ſhould be ſpared, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued among us, for ſo many years.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97664:5"/>
            <p> May he, that hath the Reſidue of the Spirit, fill ſurviving Miniſters, Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Elder, with greater meaſures of Holy Light, and Love, to furniſh us for our work, and to aſſiſt, and ſuceed us in it. May we all learn to carry it with greater <hi>Indifference</hi> to this preſent, <hi>Animal Life;</hi> and dayly advance in our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and Preparations for the <hi>Heavenly one.</hi> The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of any of our Friends, who were made meet for
<pb facs="tcp:97664:5"/>Heaven, may be many ways improved to this Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; <hi>for whom,</hi> you know, <hi>we are not to Sorrow, as others who have no Hope.</hi> Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs your late Sickneſs, and Indiſpoſition, ſince the breach God hath made in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, will be regarded as an additional Call, and help to ſuch Thoughts, and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as this Diſcourſe is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to promote. And if the many Prayers, of thoſe who have reaſon to Bleſs God for you, may be
<pb facs="tcp:97664:6"/>heard, (as in ſome Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they have been,) we may hope your Life and Serviceableneſs ſhall be yet prolong'd. In which requeſt to God, <hi>I</hi> heartily concur, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Reſpectful, tho moſt Unworthy Fellow-Servant, in the Work of the Goſpel, <hi>John Shower.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Febr.</hi> 13. 169<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:97664:6"/>
            <head>THE Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label> 
                  <hi>THe Introduction, Paraphraſe, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Text.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label> 
                  <hi>The Method and Deſign of the following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Good Men, in the Preſent State, are burdened with their Sins and Sufferings, ſo as to groan for Deliverance,</hi> p. 13.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. III.</label> 
                  <hi>They have a Certain Expectation, of a Better State and Life after this; and may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably perſwaded of their own Title in particular,</hi> p. 25.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:97664:7"/>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IV.</label> 
                  <hi>To Deſire and Long for this Bleſſed State be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Temper of a Christian Spirit,</hi> p. 33.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. V.</label> 
                  <hi>Of the Reſurrection of the Body. It is Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, Probable, and Certain. Where were the Souls of thoſe who have, been raiſed from the Dead, during their ſeparation from their Bodies? Our Reſurrection by Chriſt Illuſtrated, and proved,</hi> p. 50.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VI.</label> 
                  <hi>The ſame Body for ſubſtance, is to be raiſed again at the laſt day. What the Change will be of theſe Bodies hereafter, from what they are at preſent,</hi> p. 68.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VII.</label> 
                  <hi>Inferences of Truth, and Duty from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Diſcourſe. The Soul doth not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,
<pb facs="tcp:97664:7"/>when the Body dies. The Felicity of the Soul is that, which we principally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Our Faith ſhould be confirmed about it: Our Affections and Carriage ſhould correſpond to ſuch a Belief,</hi> p. 79.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. VIII.</label> 
                  <hi>Of the Characters of ſuch, who may, and ought to long for this Glorious Change; who they are, who have a Title to this deſired Bleſſedneſs,</hi> p. 60.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IX.</label> 
                  <hi>How Few Christians live in the Exerciſe of ſuch Deſires: What may be the Reaſon? Some fear of Death conſiſtent with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs. Elder Chriſtians, and the Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Infirm, ſhould quicken ſuch a Deſire of Deliverance. Reproof, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation in reference hereto,</hi> p. 94.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. X.</label> 
                  <hi>Our Holy Friends Departed obtain their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires by Dying: this ſhould moderate our
<pb facs="tcp:97664:8"/>funeral Sorrows. A ſhort Account of the Exemplary Character of Mrs.</hi> Mary Doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>little, <hi>with ſome Paſſages of her laſt Sickneſs. Concluſion.</hi> p. 112.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97664:8"/>
            <head>A Funeral Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 COR. V. 4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>We that are in this Tabernacle do groan, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Burdened, not for that we would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloathed, but cloathed upon, that Mortality might be ſwallowed up of Life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Introduction, Paraphraſe and Explication of the Text.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>NOtwithſtanding all the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult Exerciſes of St. <hi>Paul</hi> from Enemies on every ſide, upon the account of his Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Chriſt, in the Diſcharge of his Miniſtry; He bears up with an invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible courage and reſolution, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of an Eternal Recompence in the other World. This is the Tenor of his Diſcourſe throughout the foregoing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97664:9"/>Chapter, he begins and ends with it; and repeats it at large in the three laſt Verſes, <hi>For this cauſe we faint not,</hi> &amp;c. That is, however perplexed and perſecuted, caſt down and troubled; yet neither he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, nor any of thoſe ingaged in the ſame cauſe, and work with him, did <hi>faint in their minds;</hi> becauſe their preſent Sufferings did only prepare the way for a more glorious Reward; <hi>For our light Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,</hi> ſays he, <hi>which is but for a moment, worketh for us a more exceeding, and eternal weight of Glory; while we look not at the things which are ſeen, which are but temporal: but at the things which are not ſeen, which are Eternal.</hi> And ſuppoſing the worſt, that theſe Afflictions ſhould end in Death, yet ſuch a caſe would admit of comfort. <hi>For we know,</hi> ſays he, verſe 1.2. of this chapter, we are confidently perſwaded, upon very good grounds, <hi>that if our Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved,</hi> we have a better dwelling provided, an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier Condition in hope and view; <hi>We have a Building of God, an Houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens. And for this we groan earneſtly,</hi> for this ſtate of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Happineſs, <hi>deſiring to be cloathed upon with our Houſe, that is from Heaven.</hi> A Bleſſed State, ſo fitted for us, and we for it, that no Apparel for the Body can be more.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97664:9"/>
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>He was not only content to Dye, and ready with Patience to receive a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons out of this World; but ſo unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able was the difference, in his Judgment, between his preſent State in the Body, and that which he expected beyond the Grave, that he reckoned a Tranſlation was every way preferable, and rather to be choſen, even by intervening Death; that ſo, inſtead of this little Houſe, this mean and poor Dwelling, which we now inhabit, we may come to a better <hi>Building,</hi> that is <hi>of God,</hi> formed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by him; to the more ſpacious Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which the bleſſed God has provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for us above; that inſtead of this mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Tent, <hi>This earthly Tabernacle,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually liable to ſo many changes, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and inconveniencies, we may have a <hi>Houſe not made with hands,</hi> that is of God's immediate Work, more excellent and more laſting, more ſafe and more abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: That inſtead of this <hi>earthly Houſe</hi> of dirt and clay, into which it will ſhortly be diſſolved, we may have <hi>a building in Heaven,</hi> ſuited to the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly State and Life; a more commodious Dwelling, fitted for the Offices of a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97664:10"/>Glorified Soul, and which ſhall not mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but be <hi>Eternal,</hi> that when <hi>this Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle</hi> is diſſolved, which needs every day to be repaired, and with all our care cannot long be ſupported, we may have a permanent, unchangable building, <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in the Heavens:</hi> In ſhort, that our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as well as our Souls, may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and bleſſed, and unchangably ſo, in the other World.</p>
                  <p>After ſuch a State, and Life as this, ſo elegantly deſcribed, in the beginning of this Chapter, he declares his <hi>earneſt Deſire</hi> in this Text; not in his own name only, but as the common ſenſe of all the Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt. This he amplifies and limits, by ſeveral expreſſions, unto which ſome following verſes in this chapter will give further light; <hi>For we that are in this Tabernacle do groan, being burdened, not for that we would be uncloathed, but cloathed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Mortality might be ſwallowed up of Life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>In which words we may conſider two Parts. 1. The State and Temper of the Followers of Chriſt, or of all real Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, That while they are in the Body, they are burdened, and groan for Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97664:10"/>2. A Judicious Stating the matter of ſuch Deſire of Deliverance, Or what it is that they groan and long for, ſet forth in three expreſſions, 1. Negatively, It is <hi>not</hi> Simply <hi>to be uncloathed,</hi> But, 2. <hi>To be cloathed upon.</hi> And 3. <hi>That Mortality may be ſwallowed up of Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The ſtate and Temper of good men, or real Chriſtians, while they are in the Body, <hi>They are burdened,</hi> and therefore <hi>groan for deliverance.</hi> We that are in <hi>this earthly Tabernacle,</hi> Or, as the expreſſion is <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>While we are at home in the Body,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Body, or <hi>While we converſe and Sojourn in the Body,</hi> Which he calls <hi>an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Houſe, ver.</hi> 1. But becauſe it is no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain fixed Dwelling, he adds the other term, of <hi>a Tabernacle.</hi> While we dwell in this little Fabrick, framed at firſt out of the duſt of the earth, as were the <hi>Worms,</hi> who are therefore our Kindred and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and they were formed before the Creation of man. While we are in <hi>this earthly Tabernacle,</hi> whoſe foundation is in the duſt, Whoſe matter is not more excellent than that of the Beaſts that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. An <hi>earthly</hi> Tabernacle, not only as to its original, but is ſuſtained and repaired by earthly things,
<note place="margin">146 Pſalm. 4.12, Eccl. 7.</note> and ere long to be reſolved into <hi>Earth</hi> again; <hi>This duſt ſhall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97664:11"/>be turned to earth, as it was, and the Spirit ſhall return to God.</hi> While we are in this <hi>earthly Houſe</hi> we groan, and long for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval; we earneſtly covet, deſire and wait for,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Dwelling, and a better State; we pant, and breath, and long for it, from the Faith and Hope of what God has revealed, concerning the upper, better World, and the future Felicity of all that believe in Chriſt, where we look for another ſort of <hi>Bodies,</hi> and another kind of <hi>Life:</hi> this is that we aſpire and groan after, and would fain obtain.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. He deſcribes the matter of ſuch <hi>a Deſire,</hi> and the juſt limits of it, in three Expreſſions. 1. <hi>Negatively, Not for that we would be uncloathed;</hi> i. e. 1. <hi>Not Simply to dye,</hi> for dying ſake; Not meerly to be rid of the Body, and to live without any: As we are a ſort of Creatures made up of Soul and body, the ſeparation of theſe two cannot in it ſelf, for its own ſake, be deſirable; we have a natural, innocent, unavoidable Averſion to <hi>Death,</hi> as ſuch; And as it is a Penalty, and the fruit of Sin, (as even to the beſt man it is,) there cannot but be ſome unwillingneſs to dye,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97664:11"/>however fit it be to be deſired otherwiſe, on the account of the Conſequences of Death. All the Faith and Reaſon in the world cannot make Death to be no <hi>penalty,</hi> So neither is it poſſible that any man can reaſon or believe himſelf into a love of Pain and Death as ſuch. Therefore it is not ſimply <hi>to be uncloathed,</hi> to have Soul and Body ſeparated, that is here deſired. It is not a perpetual ſtate of being <hi>without a Body;</hi> For he deſires to be <hi>cloathed upon,</hi> and <hi>not found naked.</hi> Our caſe is ſo ſtated, that our Souls are to be cloathed upon with a Body, and we cannot but deſire that the union of the Soul and body ſhould be preſerved; and in the ſtate of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there is ſome hankering of the Soul after the body, Some ſuch Deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining that Reunion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. Neither is it meerly <hi>a Wearineſs of this preſent Life,</hi> by reaſon of the Burden of ſorrows and Sufferings, which the Apoſtle and other Chriſtians met with in it, that makes them thus to <hi>groan:</hi> For if he might be further ſerviceable to the intereſt of Chriſt, and therein be accepted and pleaſing to him, he declares, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. that he was willing to live. He profeſſes his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97664:12"/>readineſs to prefer <hi>the Salvation</hi> of <hi>many Souls,</hi> and his being inſtrumental to their <hi>happineſs,</hi> before the haſtening of <hi>his own.</hi> He knew that God may have as much Service in our Lives, in an afflicted ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing State, as in a proſperous Condition; he knew That we may glorifie God in Sickneſs, and in a Priſon, as much, or more than in health or liberty? And that to bear any of our Trials and Burdens well, and to honour God by a Chriſtian Deportment under them, is better than to be delivered. His <hi>Deſire</hi> therefore to <hi>the bleſſed State,</hi> which was in expectation, was not to the Act of Diſſolution it ſelf, without reference to what would follow. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires not ſo much the end of <hi>this Life,</hi> whatever he now ſuffered, as the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>the next Life;</hi> which he hoped for. It was not <hi>an Annihilation,</hi> to put a period to his preſent ſufferings, but a happy <hi>Change,</hi> which he groan'd for; Not a Ruin, but a temporary diſſolution of this earthly Houſe, in order to an Eternal Advantage; Not a bare privation of <hi>this</hi> Life, but a paſſage to a <hi>better.</hi> He doth not groan ſo much, from the Senſe of <hi>preſent Evil,</hi> as by reaſon of the <hi>Abſence</hi> of his <hi>moſt deſired Good.</hi> He was not ſo much burdened by what he felt, and could not avoid, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move, as by what he foreſaw and expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97664:12"/>and could not yet Enjoy: He muſt dye firſt, and have the old Houſe pull'd down, before he could reach that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Felicity, which he ſo earneſtly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires after.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. It is therefore further expreſt, as that which he groaned and longed for, viz. <hi>to be Cloathed upon;</hi> To lay aſide this mean and little, troubleſome Garment, for a more beautiful and commodious one; To have this earthly Houſe diſſolved, and moulder into duſt, with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of reaſſuming <hi>Another,</hi> or <hi>the Same with a glorious Change.</hi> And in that ſenſe the Expreſſion, <hi>verſe</hi> 3. may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. That <hi>being thus cloathed,</hi> that is, with ſuch a glorified Body, <hi>we may not be found Naked,</hi> or without any Body at all. Though
<note n="*" place="bottom">A. B. <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. Vol. Serm. 6th.</note> ſome carry the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>Deſiring to be cloathed upon,</hi> as wiſhing not to put off this Body at all, but to be in the number of thoſe, who ſhall be <hi>found alive at the coming of Chriſt to Judgment,</hi> which ſome of the Diſciples of Chriſt expected, by a miſtake of what
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97664:13"/>he ſaid concerning St. <hi>John, If I will that he tarry till I come.</hi> And ſo the words may be read, <hi>If ſo be that we ſhall be found cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not naked;</hi> That is, if at Chriſt's coming we ſhall be found <hi>Alive,</hi> and not <hi>Dead;</hi> and ſo have this mortal corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Body, changed into a Spiritual Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and Immortal one, without Dying. Whether that was the ſenſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, or not, I ſhall diſcourſe of theſe words, as the common Sentiment of real Chriſtians, who have no hope of Living till the end of the World, but expect to dye e're it be long, and carneſtly deſire a future Bleſſedneſs for Soul and Body in another Life; and therefore when they lay down this Body in the Duſt, they <hi>groan to be cloathed upon,</hi> to have theſe vile Bodies made like the glorious Body of Chriſt; or, as the Apoſtle himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.53.</note> To have <hi>this Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible put on Incorruption, and this Mortal put on Immortality.</hi> The <hi>putting off</hi> there, is the ſame with the <hi>being cloathed upon</hi> here. That is, they groan to have this preſent State changed for the Felicity and Glory of that future State, which Chriſt hath given them to expect, both for Soul and Body in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97664:13"/>
                  <head>SECT. VII.</head>
                  <p n="3">3. There is yet another Expreſſion, which riſeth higher, <hi>That Mortality may be ſwallowed up of Life.</hi> That which is Mortal.
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>This our mortal Life,</hi> which is ſubject to Dangers, Afflictions and Death it ſelf, That this may be <hi>Swallowed up of Life,</hi> as is that which is Imperfect, by that which is Perfect; as Infancy and Childhood by Maturity and Manhood, or as Darkneſs is ſwallowed up in Light. The mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that our low Animal Life may be changed into an Heavenly one; that our frail, ſhort, and tranſitory Life may be changed into an Immortal, Eternal one; that the Corruption and Mortality, which our Bodies are liable to, and which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in them while they are in the Grave, may be removed; Or, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Apoſtles Phraſe, <hi>That Death may be ſwallowed up in Victory,</hi> may be finally, perfectly, and <hi>for ever Deſtroyed:</hi> For ſo the expreſſion does import, and is often rendered in other places,
<note n="*" place="bottom">See Dr. <hi>Hammond.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54. g.</note> 
                     <hi>for ever:</hi> And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97664:14"/>that includes the Reſurrection of the <hi>Body</hi> to an happy State, as one part of this Deſire. For if by Dying we are more miſerable than before, <hi>Death</hi> is not ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in <hi>Victory,</hi> it rather is too hard for <hi>us,</hi> and gains a <hi>Victory over us.</hi> But if our ſtate be bettered by <hi>Death,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as to our Souls, but our very <hi>Bodies</hi> are alſo to be raiſed again to a glorious Life; if when <hi>Death</hi> hath done its utmoſt, our Souls paſs into a State of Reſt and Bliſs, to be compleated in <hi>a glorious Reſurrection of the Body,</hi> and to be continued and increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all Eternity; we are then <hi>Victorious</hi> over <hi>Death, Death</hi> may be ſaid to be <hi>ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in Victory, or Mortality ſwallowed up of Everlaſting Life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97664:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Method and Deſign of the following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Good men in the preſent ſtate are burdened with their Sins, and Sufferings, ſo as to groan for Deliverance.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>After this Paraphraſe and Explication of the words, that which I deſign as the Ground of my following diſcourſe, is this, <hi>That it becomes the State, and Frame, of real Chriſtians, while they are burdened in theſe mortal Bodies, earneſtly to deſire a better, an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Life, wherein the Body, as well as the Soul, ſhall be gloriouſly Changed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In diſcourſing of this, I ſhall <hi>firſt</hi> ſhow, That ſuch is the preſent State of good men in theſe Bodies, that they groan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der manifold Burdens, that may well make them long for Deliverance. II. That they have the certain Expectation of a better State and Life, after the diſſolution of this earthly Tabernacle by Death. III. That it is agreeable to the Temper of a Chriſtian Spirit, ſo far as renewed and ſanctified, to long for that better State and Life, beyond the Grave. IV. That it is not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97664:15"/>ſuch a State and Life, wherein they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be without any Body at all; but to have <hi>their Bodies</hi> raiſed, and changed, and glorified; To be cloathed upon with an Houſe from Heaven, and to have mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality ſwallowed up in Life. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of theſe particulars will make way for the practical Application, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to this ſolemn Occaſion, on which I am deſired to preach on this Text.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, That ſuch is the preſent ſtate of good Men in theſe Bodies, that they groan under manifold <hi>Burdens,</hi> which may well make them long for Deliverance. I need not run far into the common Theme of the Miſeries of humane Life, which every one feels, or knows of thoſe that do: Our Sufferings and our Sins, while in this earthly Tabernacle, will be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to be conſidered under this head.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Our <hi>Sorrows,</hi> and <hi>Sufferings,</hi> while in the Body. Our early Tears when we come into the World prognoſticate a good ſhare of theſe to be expected. Not to mention the Vexation of diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in our Temporal Injoyments, as a great part of this Burden; the actual Sorrows and Afflictions which all partake
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97664:15"/>of, are very many, and great, heavy and afflictive; they are ſuch as extort the Cries, and Tears, and Complaints, of all ſorts of Perſons. The little plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and joy we meet with, is mixed with an alloy of Sorrow; but our Sorrows are more numerous, weighty, and unmix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; many ſad Occurrences, vexing Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions painful and afflictive Diſeaſes, every week diſquiet us. Cares conſume us, Fears devours us. Grief ſcizeth us every way, and ſometimes from ſuch Evils, as nothing but the Hope of Heaven can ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port us under: No other balm can cure ſome of our Wounds. So that <hi>evil,</hi> as well as <hi>few, are the days of the years of our Pilgrimage;</hi> and the <hi>preſent World,</hi> on thisaccount,
<note place="margin">47. <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. 1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.</note> may well be called <hi>an evil World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The very Neceſſities, Infirmities and Pains of <hi>the Body</hi> are a continual Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, even ſuch as belong to our <hi>Humanity,</hi> and are common to Men; beſides the many more and greater, we are often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to as Chriſtians, for the ſake of Chriſt, and the Profeſſion of the Truth, to Indignities and Injuries of all ſorts, from the Malice of the Devil and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted World, whom he uſeth as his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments. But we need not other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97664:16"/>to fail us, and Friends to grieve us, or Enemies to hate us, or Satan to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt us, or the World to deceive us; this very <hi>Body,</hi> this earthly Houſe, is ſubject to ſo many Calamities, as may make us weary of it, and groan to be delivered. How much of our time muſt it take up! How much pains and labour muſt we be at about it! How much grief and ſorrow muſt it undergo! How many ways do pain and ſickneſs enter! By every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and every part of the Body, and this is communicated to the Whole, and we cannot but feel it. If the body be pincht with hunger and thirſt, the Soul is reſtleſs till it procure a ſupply: If the one be ſick, the other is ſad. The Soul is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the wants of the Body, and for the moſt part Inordinately, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Thoughtful, and calls out the Soul to attend upon the ſeveral Paſſions of the Body, filling it with Deſires, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Griefs, Fears, Angers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which hinder our Knowledg of God, ſervice of him, and Communion with him. Is it any wonder if they that do ſo, groan to put off the Shooe that pinches them, that they may be Weary, and Pained, and cold, and thirſty, afflicted and griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no more? Can we find this preſent dwelling ſo very inconvenient, and not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97664:16"/>deſire to have ſomething better? Do we not find the
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>See Mr.</hi> S. S. <hi>Farewel to Life,</hi> p. 145. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> Body a clog to the Soul, when it would run; a Manacle to the Soul, that would work; a ſnare to the Soul that would be free; a Fetter to chain it to Earthly and Material things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Do we not own theſe and the like Burdens to be innumerable, heavy, and inevitable, and is it ſtrange we ſhould long for Eaſe? How ſmall a Portion of Time is it, wherein our own Sickneſs, or that of our Relations and Frends, doth not diſquiet us! Their Afflictions, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and Sufferings, or our own, are continual Burdens; and the more we love them, the more we are intereſted in what concerns them, and the greater part we bear in their Sufferings, as being the more affected with their Miſeries. And yet God knows all this is needful to keep down the Love of this World, take off our undue Affections to Earthly things, and raiſe our Thoughts to ſomething o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and better, than is here to be had.</p>
                  <p>O! How many do we know, and have known, who groan under theſe Burdens from the Diſorders and Pains of the Body, as the Harbingers of Death! Eſpecially
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97664:17"/>under the weakneſs, Languiſhing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays of <hi>Old Age:</hi> For even a Diſeaſed and Conſumed Body in that caſe, tho it be leſs Tempting, is not the leſs troubleſome, but the more ſo, even to make them weary of Life.</p>
                  <p>Our days are grief and ſorrow, trouble and affliction, that we may be made to know we are not at home, but ſtrangers here; while <hi>Iſrael</hi> dwelt in a fruitful <hi>Goſhen,</hi> they might be Tempted to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Promiſed Land, but their Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, Dangers and Conflicts in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs would not ſuffer 'em to miſtake a Deſart for a <hi>Canaan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>What is the daily condition of our Fleſh, as
<note n="*" place="bottom">Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> of Self-denial. <hi>Chap.</hi> 38,</note> one well expreſſes it, but Weakneſs and Suffering, with Care and Labour to prevent much worſe, which yet we know cannot be avoided? The Sorrow of many a Man's Life has made him wiſh he had never been born; and why ſhould he not be as willing to dye, which doth ten thouſand times more for him, if he be a real Chriſtian, than to be unborn would have done. Not a Relation ſo comfortable, but hath its diſcomforts. Not a Friend ſo ſuitable,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97664:17"/>but hath ſome diſcordancy; nor any ſo amiable and ſweet, but hath ſomething troubleſome and bitter; not a place ſo pleaſant and commodious, but hath its unfitneſs and diſcommodities; Not a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety ſo good and regular, but hath its Corruptions and Irregularities. And ſhould we be loath to leave ſuch a Life as this? When the Fruit is Ripe, ſhould it not be Gathered? When the Corn is Ripe, would you have it grow there, and not be Cut? When we are begotten again to the hopes of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, ſhould we be ſo deſirous to ſtay in the Womb? Is it not another kind of Life which we ſhall have with God? Are they not purer Comforts that ſtay for us above? But if you will not have the Grapes to be Gathered and Preſt, how can you expect to have the Wine? Methinks our Fleſh ſhould have enough e're this time of Sickneſs, and Pain, and Want, and Croſſes, and ſhould be contented to lye down in hope of the Day when theſe ſhall be no more.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p n="2">II. Upon the account of <hi>Sin</hi> they are yet more <hi>burdened.</hi> The frequent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin, the fears of unpardoned ſin,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97664:18"/>the remainders of Indwelling ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are a conſtant burden to a Chriſtian while in the Body. They are ſenſible how ſhort and ſmall, how weak and low, their Knowledg of God, and Love to him are; how imperfectly and defectively they ſerve him here, in compariſon of what their Bretheren above do: And they are ſenſible, that much of this ariſes from the <hi>Body,</hi> that it is no wonder if they are willing to be <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncloathed.</hi> They find it not only a troubleſome, but a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Companion, as that which hinders them from many hours Communion with God; that clogs, and diverts, and interrupts their Service of God, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of him: So that even the beſt and
<note n="*" place="bottom">Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> Dying Thoughts, p. 78.</note> holieſt Men have owned they had much ado to refrain from wiſhing they had never been born, even when at the ſame time they knew that thought to be ſinful. The intereſt of this Body ſtands in ſuch competition with God and our Souls, ſince the entrance of ſin; we are expoſed, and tempted, and drawn to ſin, ſo many ways by means of the Body by our Senſes, Appetites, and Imagination, as may juſtly make us groan for Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97664:18"/>All the objects of ſenſe about us in every Condition, our Food, and Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, our Houſes and Eſtates, Friends and Relations, and our Selves, moſt of all, yeild us Temptations. And the more Holy and Sanctified any are, the more apprehenſive they muſt needs be of this Burthen; their Spirits are more tender, Earthly things are more unſuitable, God's diſpleaſure is more Fear'd, ſo that they would rather chuſe to be freed from ſin, than to be Poſſeſſors of the whole World. The clearer Light they have of the evil of Sin, and the more unfeigned their Love to God and Chriſt is, who is diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and diſpleaſed by it, and the more ardent their Deſires are, to be like him, and pleaſe him, and the more lively their Hopes are of living with him for ever, this makes this Burthen of Sin to be ſo much the more intolerable.</p>
                  <p>And even Temptations to ſin, tho they prevail not, are a part of their Burden; it is grievous to a good man to be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſollicited and tempted by the World, Fleſh, and Devil, to diſhonour and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Lord. And where are we with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch Temptation? We can hardly open our Eyes and Ears, but we meet with one.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97664:19"/>
                  <p> So that this is one great conſideration that moves them to deſire, and chuſe to be diſſolved, that they may ſin no more, and be tempted no more, that they may grieve the Spirit of Grace no more, and interrupt their own Peace, and Joy, and Communion with God and Chriſt, no more for ever.</p>
                  <p>Yea, notwithſtanding the Mortification of the Fleſh, and the Life of Faith ſincerely begun, and carried on; yet the ſinful di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of our Spirits, our frequent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays and back-ſlidings, our low attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Grace and Comfort, are owing very much to <hi>this Body,</hi> as the Spring, or at leaſt the occaſion of them; our ſloth and negligence, our eager Paſſions, inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Cares, and Fears, and Griefs, yea, our general Diſinclination and Averſion to Spiritual and Heavenly things, are much from this fleſh, this earthly Houſe of our Tabernacle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>Let me ſum up this Head, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent words of
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Howe, <hi>of Bleſſedneſs,</hi> p. 493.</note> another on this Subject. <q>Who can reflect, <hi>ſays he,</hi> upon this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97664:19"/>State, and not be in pangs and groans after a better? Eſpecially on the account of the Spiritual Grievances of Chriſtians, the darkneſs of our becloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed minds, the glimmering and ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Apprehenſions we have of the moſt important things, the inconſiſtency of our ſcattered Thoughts when we would apply them to Spiritual Objects, the great difficulty of working off <hi>an ill frame of Heart,</hi> and the no leſs difficulty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a <hi>good one,</hi> our being ſo often toſt as between Heaven and Hell, that when we have been raiſed, and hope to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend no more, we are all on a ſuddain plunged in the Ditch, ſo that our own Cloaths abhor us. How often do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd Temptations return again, and vanquiſhed Corruptions recover ſtrength, that we know not when our work is done! We are miſerable that we need be always watching, and more miſerable that we cannot watch, but are ſo often ſurpriſed and overcome of evil. We ſay ſometimes we will ſeek relief in Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but we cannot Retire from our ſelves; Or in converſe with Godly Friends, but they often prove Snares to us, and we to them, or we hear but our own Sins and Miſeries repeared in their Complaints. Would we Pray, how
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97664:20"/>faint is the Breath we utter! How long is it e're we can get our Hearts poſſeſt, with any becoming Apprehenſions of God, or lively ſenſe of our own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments! So for <hi>Meditation,</hi> when we would compoſe our Thoughts, we may as well attempt to hold the Wind in our fiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> And would we then out of Choice continue in ſuch a ſtate as this, under ſo many Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and of ſuch a Nature? How is it that we do not cry out more feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, <hi>O wretched man that I am! Who ſhall deliver me from this Body of Death?</hi> Nothing but the belief and Expectation of another and better ſtate can ſupport us under theſe Burdens; and that is next to be conſidered.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97664:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Chriſtians have a certain Expectation of a better State and Life after this; and may be comfortably perſuaded of their own Title in particular.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> THat real Chriſtians have the certain Expectation of a better State and Life, after the Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Earthly Tabernable. 1. As to the thing it ſelf, ſuch a better State is Certain. 2. As to Particular Chriſtians, they may have a certain Expectation of it, as to themſelves. Let us Conſider,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Objective Certainty,</hi> That there is ſuch a better State, and Life beyond the Grave. Were there no ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, of all Creatures in the World, Men were the moſt Miſerable, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Chriſtians, and the Wiſeſt and moſt Knowing Men, would be
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>See</hi> Mr. How's <hi>Vanity of Man as Mortal.</hi>
                     </note> moſt ſo
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97664:21"/>The preſent Vanity of Life were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make us regret it, if nothing more or better were to be expected, we could not but always live in dread and fear of Death; we ſhould not enjoy our ſelves here, and yet would be afraid of loſing our ſelves for ever hereafter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>Parker,</hi> Demonſtration of the Law of Nature, <hi>Sect.</hi> xxi.</note> 
                     <q>We were miſerable indeed in this Life, if there were no ſuch Future State of Immortality to be expected. From the higheſt pitch of humane Felicity, there could be nothing but a ſad proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the gloomy Regions of Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Death and Darkneſs. What can ſupport the mind under ſuch a view? Or ſcatter our black and Melancholy Apprehenſions about it? When we think that after a ſhort Muſhrome Life, we muſt return to Duſt and Silence, and be for ever buried in the horror and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſs of the Grave. This will daſh and diſturb all our Joys, and ſpoil the Cheerfulneſs and Tranquility of our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in a proſperous State. This will double all the Miſeries of Life, for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them to think to fetch relief from dying, is ſuch another kind of Comfort,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97664:21"/>as if you ſhould tell a Man in a Storm at Sea, that there is no hope of allaying the Tempeſt, but when you are Drown'd, the Storm will trouble you no longer. This will be an intolerable Acceſſion to the load of preſent calamity, to conſider the Period of Life is ſo ſhort and Fading, and that ſo much of ſo little ſhould be loſt and worn away in Sorrow and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and to deſpair of any Remedy or Deliverance, but in Eternal Death. 'Tis much more Eligible never to have been born, than only to Grieve, and ſuffer a while, and Dye; to drop a Tear, and vent a Groan, and paſs a little time in a Stor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Tempeſtuous World, and then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appear, and ſink back into Nothing.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But all who own any thing of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, acknowledg ſomewhat of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal State; the poor Heathens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had ſome notices of it; the Jews in their ſeveral Generations believed it: and the very Light of Nature will do much to manifeſt that ſuch a difference there will be hereafter between a Man and a Beaſt, between the Good and Bad, between the final State of thoſe that love, and pleaſe, and ſerve God, and of thoſe that diſobey his known will. For who can acknowledg and own a God, as Maker and Governour of the World, the Wiſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97664:22"/>and Righteous Judge of all, and think he will turn Men promiſcuouſly into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or Hell at random, without diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing between Friends and Enemies, Righteous and wicked; or that he'l neither Reward or Puniſh; that there ſhall be no ſtate of Happineſs for the one ſort, or of Miſery for the other. Beſides the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Conſcience, as to the Hopes and Fears of theſe things in another World, is of weight in this caſe.</p>
                  <p>But I hope I need not here be large, when I ſpeak to ſuch as profeſs to believe the Bible: and <hi>there</hi> it is as certain as that God is true, who hath declared it; or that Chriſt was ſent of God, who has taught it; as true, as that he died, and roſe again, and aſcended to Heaven; and that all his Apoſtles and Followers have lived and died in the Expectation of ſuch a State. The Reſurrection of the body, I grant, was not ſo plain an Article before the coming of Chriſt; but a general ſtate of Happineſs for Holy Perſons in another World no Chriſtians will deny: And our Lord has proved the perſonal Capacity of future Rewards, by the Doctrine of the Immortality of the Soul, and the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body, and by an account of the manner of the Adminiſtration of theſe Rewards, as more inchoate and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97664:22"/>at Death, more univerſal and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate at Judgment, in the great day of Retribution. All the Doctrines of the Goſpel concerning Chriſt, do ſuppoſe or aſcertain this. He came into the World to purchaſe our Right and Title to ſuch a bleſſed State, and went to Heaven again, to plead, and proſecute, and apply, and beſtow it. So that ſuch a thing is <hi>Certain,</hi> and may be expected, by all, the Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Chriſt. It is as certain and unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable as the Word and Oath of God can make it: much more Certain, than if a Meſſenger from the Dead did come and tell you ſo: For the manifold witneſſes of the Holy Ghoſt to the Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Chriſt, and the truth of the Goſpel, is a much greater thing, and more credible, than any ſuch tranſient Teſtimony could be. But I ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on this, the Devils themſelves believe it, and prove it; for if there be no Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, there is no Hell.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Particular Chriſtians may have a certain Expectation of this happy State beyond the Grave. <hi>We know,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>that we have a Building in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> when this earthly Tabernacle ſhall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97664:23"/>be diſſolved. <hi>We know,</hi> and <hi>are aſſured of it;</hi> It is a thing ſo evident and manifeſt, it is capable of being demonſtrated. It is not my bare Opinion, but the common ſenſe of all the Followers of Chriſt, built on ſuch grounds, that we are ready to venture our Lives, and all that is dear to us, upon this believing Expectation. And becauſe we know we have another better Building reſerved in Heaven for us, we therefore groan and long to be there; we <hi>have</hi> a Building in Heaven, though we are yet on Earth: As he that hath an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in another Kingdom or Country, may call both <hi>his own,</hi> though he cannot dwell in both at once; nay though it may be he muſt travel a great way, and croſs the Seas, before he can reach to one of them.</p>
                  <p>Particular Chriſtians may be certain. The Apoſtle often declares it as to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all the Children of God have a Title to the Inheritance, they have Deeds and Evidences to ſhow for it, they have the Will and Teſtament of their Lord and Maſter to produce, and they have <hi>the Seal of his Spirit,</hi> as a witneſs in their Hearts, which is <hi>the Earneſt of the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whereby they are ſealed to the day of Redemption.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97664:23"/>
                  <p> Sanctifying Grace is called an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, Incorruptible Seed,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.13.</note> and they that are partakers of it <hi>have Eternal Life abiding in them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 John 3.13.</note> becauſe this preſent Life begun ſhall be perfected in Glory. This Seal of the Holy Spirit on the Soul, is the <hi>Earneſt</hi> of the heavenly Inheritance, to manifeſt how ſure and certain it is, as well as a <hi>foretaſte</hi> to prove how good. <hi>We have an Houſe in Heaven,</hi> a Building not made with hands. We have it as <hi>our own,</hi> we are ſo certain of it, as we reckon our ſelves in ſome ſenſe already in Poſſeſſion. We abide, it is true, for a while in this earthly Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; but we have another and a better Houſe, a Building of God, not made with Hands, and we long to be there.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>They that can make out the unfeigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Faith in Chriſt, and the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of their Love to him; who can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the truth of their Sanctification, who can perceive the Image of God upon their Souls, his Impreſs, Character and Seal, having turned their Hearts from the World and Sin, to God, and Holineſs, and Heaven, with an anſwerable Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97664:24"/>in Simplicity and Godly Sincerity; they may have a ſubjective Certainty of this, by the Teſtimony of Conſcience, and the concurrent Witneſs of the Spirit, enabling them to diſcern the Truth of their Grace: they may know their own intereſt in the Promiſe, and argue it to their Comfort, from the qualifications of ſuch to whom the Promiſe is made. I do not ſay that All do reach to an actual Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, and full perſwaſion; the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity we find do not; but ſuch a thing is attainable, and all ſhould Labour after it: And did we ſeek it in the right way, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring, by the exerciſe and increaſe of Grace, to know the truth of it, more would reach this, than commonly do; And then more would long, and groan, and deſire to be uncloathed of this Earthly Tabernacle, that they may be cloathed upon with an Houſe from Heaven, and Mortality be ſwallowed up of Life. Which brings me to conſider the <hi>Third</hi> thing I propoſed to ſpeak to.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:97664:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>To deſire and long for a bleſſed State and Life beyond the Grave, proved to be ſuitable to the Temper of a Chriſtian Spirit.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p n="3">III. THat it is ſuitable to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of a Chriſtian Spirit, ſo far as renewed and ſanctified, to deſire and long for that better State and Life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Grave. I know there may be an impatient Senſe of preſent troubles, or an inordinate Fear of threatning Dangers and Calamities, that may make ſome ſinfully deſire to be uncloathed, make them long for Death, and be glad to find the Grave. <hi>O Lord, I beſeech thee,</hi> ſays Jonah,
<note place="margin">4. Jonah 3.</note> 
                     <hi>take away my Life from me, for it is better for me to die than to live. And my Soul chuſeth ſtrangling rather than Life,</hi> ſays <hi>Job.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">7. <hi>Job</hi> 15.</note> But that is not the caſe here, the Apoſtle goes upon another Principle; he groaned, while in this Tabernacle, for the glorious State which he believingly foreſaw. And eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry renewed Soul has a dipoſition ſo to do,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97664:25"/>in his new Nature, he is <hi>born from above,</hi> and his very principles have a tendency to <hi>Heaven,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> he is attempered and ſuited to the heavenly State: by that very Grace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are made Chriſtians, we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed to look for, and wait for, the glorious appearance of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, at which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance we hope to be cloathed upon with an Houſe from Heaven: <hi>For when he who is our Life ſhall appear,</hi> he has promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>we alſo ſhall appear in Glory.</hi> They cannot but deſire and long for this, if they had no burden of Afflictions and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows in the World, that made them groan for deliverance: For I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that all the Conflicts and Exerciſes of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> either by bodily pains, or with enraged malicious Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, never wrung ſuch a ſigh from him, as the conflict with his own Corruptions, <hi>O wretched Man that I am!</hi> All the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that he ever met with in his earthly Tabernacle, never made him groan ſo much, as the burden of his own impure Fleſh, and his lamented diſtance from the Lord. Therefore conſider,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97664:25"/>
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, The Diſpoſition of a ſanctified Soul, as renewed by the holy Spirit, does incline and fit for this. II. The want of full Conformity to Chriſt. III. The Senſe of our Diſtance from Him, while we are here. IV. The unequal Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications of Light, and Grace, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from God and Chriſt, which a real Chriſtian doth now Experience, will aſſiſt theſe Deſires, and make him groan for Deliverance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is ſuch <hi>a Diſpoſition</hi> in the Soul, ſanctified by Divine Grace, from whence ſuch Deſires muſt needs reſult. They have received the <hi>firſt Fruits of the Spirit</hi> as the <hi>Earneſt</hi> of more, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>groan within themſelves, waiting for the Adoption, even the Redemption of the Body, Rom.</hi> 8.23. They are now taken into Gods Family, as his Children, are born from above: But the moſt ſolemn Act of their <hi>Adoption,</hi> is at the laſt day, when there ſhall be a full and final Deliverance from all penal and afflictive Evil. Called the Redemption of <hi>the Body,</hi> as Death is the laſt Enemy to be deſtroyed; and the Body, till the Reſurrection, is under the power of Death: Called <hi>a Redemption,</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:97664:26"/>becauſe it is done by vertue of the price, and ranſom which Chriſt hath paid for us. Having received the firſt Fruits of the Spirit, they groan for the Adoption, this Redemption of the Body. And <hi>by this Spirit,</hi> they are ſaid to be <hi>ſealed unto the day of Redemption,</hi> Eph. 4.30. The holy Spirit aſſures us of ſuch a day. We are now the Temples of the holy Ghoſt, and he will not leave his own Dwelling conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in the duſt. And by this holy Spirit all our Deſires and Hopes of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reſurrection are wrought in us. And the mighty Change which is made by the Spirit. on the Souls of Believers, will evidence the poſſibility of that Change which is expected as to their Bodies: For to raiſe a dead Soul to ſpiritual Life, is at leaſt an equal Inſtance, of glorious Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as to raiſe the Body from the Grave.</p>
                  <p>This they may well groan for, as the moſt ſolemn act of their Adoption, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to Chriſt their Head, who, (as ſome obſerve,) though he were the Son of God by his marvellous Conception, and owned to be ſo during his Life, yet had the higheſt Declaration of it at his Reſurrection; <hi>Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee.</hi> In like manner, though be Followers of Chriſt are now owned and treated as Children; yet the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97664:26"/>moſt publick Declaration of the Divine favour towards them, will be at the laſt day, when their Bodies ſhall be raiſed, and all the Children of the Reſurrection ſhall be born in a day. They are now made <hi>meet</hi> by the Spirit, to be partakers of the heavenly Inheritance, 1 <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 12. they are now changed into the divine Image, prepared and fitted for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly State; their Spiritual Life is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the delights and comforts of the other World, as the Animal Life is by thoſe of the preſent World. They know ſomewhat of the Excellency of it, they find ſomething in themſelves that makes them value and deſire it; and by the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Experience they have had, of the Pleaſure and Joy of obeying God, and converſing with him, they conclude how unſpeakably better it will be hereafter, when their Union and Communion ſhall be compleat.</p>
                  <p>The holy Nature they partake of by <hi>Regeneration,</hi> as mindful of its divine Original, doth mount the Soul to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, tends to the place from whence it came, works towards its Center, and makes them reſtleſs in their deſires after it; and by frequent, lively, believing thoughts of the heavenly Inheritance, they gradually enter into it; and ripen
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97664:27"/>for <hi>Glory,</hi> the nearer they come to the full Poſſeſſion. We read of being <hi>changed from Glory to Glory,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the divine Image. So that as <hi>Grace</hi> increaſeth, <hi>Glory</hi> haſteneth on, and every degree of Grace is a ſtep nearer to Glory: For the more conformable we are to the divine Image, the more meet are we to dwell with God: And he that hath fitted the new Nature to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Life, will not fail to bring his Children to it, when he has <hi>wrought them for this felf ſame thing, and given them the Earneſt of his Spirit,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6.</p>
                  <p>The new Nature, ſaith one, does as naturally aſcend to Heaven, when un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloathed of Fleſh, and hath left all the Relicks of Corruption behind it, as the pure flame aſpires into the Air, and ſeems to long to inbody it ſelf with the Sun the Fountain of Light. By this they have a fitneſs for Heaven and a <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> for that bleſſed Life, which, as it daily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, muſt make their deſires ſtronger to enter upon it. For there is a Beauty in the divine Image, and a ſweetneſs in our imperfect Graces, in the preſent Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of 'em, that muſt make us value and deſire Perfection. There is an Heavenly Sweetneſs in every Act of love to God and Chriſt, that may make the Soul cry out,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97664:27"/>oh! how happy ſhould I be, could I but love as much, and as long as I would; could I be all Love, and alway Loving, might my God and Saviour be my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant deſire, delight, and Joy! I would not envy the Honours or Pleaſures of any in this World, what then is that bleſſed State which I now hope for with perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Graces in the preſence of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>If our <hi>Faith</hi> be true, ſo as to unite us to Chriſt, and make us ſoundly believe the Goſpel Revelation, and conſent to be his, our Affections muſt needs be kindled to a willingneſs, and deſire to be with him: And if our <hi>Hope</hi> be of the right kind, it muſt be an Expectation with deſire and pleaſure, of the great and glorious things that we pretend to hope for. We are framed, and <hi>wrought by the Spirit of God, for this very ſame thing,</hi> and by continual influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from the ſame Spirit, will the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal bleſſedneſs of the future State be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on. But we cannot be meet for it, without deſiring it, we cannot prepare for it without longing after it: Preparing Grace is to make us willing of Glory, as well as meet for it, and to keep us in the way to it. And all our Diligence and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97664:28"/>Activity, all our Watchfulneſs and Care, all our Patience and Self-denial, all our Stedfaſtneſs and Perſeverande, in the Chriſtian Courſe, as the Fruits of Faith and Love, muſt be influenced, cheriſhed, and maintained, by ſuch defires. This is the deſign and tendency of all the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the holy Spirit on the Soul, for which he is promis'd and given to Believers. This is one great End of all the Ordinances and Inſtitutions of the Goſpel, under the Agency of the Holy Spirit, to qualifie and diſpoſe us for the heavenly State, and to excite and keep alive <hi>Deſires</hi> after it, and help us to purſue the proper Ends and Uſes of Life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>Secondly, Our want of full Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and Likeneſs unto Chriſt, makes theſe Deſires ſuitable to the temper of real Chriſtians. Though the guilt of Sin be removed by pardoning Grace, yet they are not perfectly cleanſed from all Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; there are ſad remainders of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual and earthly Affections. Though the reigning power of Sin be broken, by the Spirit of Holineſs, yet we are not wholly rid of it; we ſenſibly feel Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in our Mind, Diſorder in our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97664:28"/>Diſtempers in our Spirits: The moſt righteous Souls are now vexed with their own Corruption from within, and the guilt of many actual Sins, as well as by the Abominations of others. While we are in the Body, we are in a State of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and conflict. We feelingly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the inward conteſt and diviſion between the Law of the Fleſh, and the Law of the Mind, as <hi>Rebecca</hi> felt the Twins, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſtirring in her Womb. Our time of Triumph is not in this World: The troubled Sea of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup Nature will often ſend forth Mire and Dirt; but the Blood of Chriſt ſhall perfectly cleauſe us from Sin, ſo as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all our Filth, and fully deliver us from Corruption, as well as from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
                  <p>The holieſt Saints do now walk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with God under the ſenſe of remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Corruption, they watch, and pray, and ſtrive againſt it, endeavouring grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Mortification, preſſing after more Holineſs; and therefore long for <hi>Heaven,</hi> when the Deliverance will be perfect. They are now ſenſible of the workings and contrary tendency of the two oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Principles, <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> they find that the more ſpiritual any duty is, the more backward their Hearts are to it;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97664:29"/>they perceive every little indulgence of the Fleſh raiſeth an interpoſition between God and the Soul, and hinders the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, boldneſs, confidence, activity and peace, which otherwiſe they might have; they deſire and endeavour nearer Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the divine Pattern, as well as clearer evidence of Forgiveneſs. They would feign be more like God, as well as eſcape his wrath; and be delivered from Sin, as well as from Hell: They are ſenſible how Indwelling Sin indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them for holy Duties deadens and diſtracts their Hearts in ſpiritual Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, makes them loſe the benefit of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, renders Sabbaths and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Lifeleſs, and unprofitable. They feel it to be the Fewel of many a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and a conſtant root of bitterneſs, that oppoſes the Spirit of Grace, and keeps them Low, and makes them bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and unfruitful; that prevails frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by ſuddain and violent Motions, to the diſhonour of God, and the grieving of the Holy Spirit, and the reproach of their Profeſſion; and ſo ſhakes their Peace, and damps their Aſſurance, and obſtructs their comfortable Hopes of Gods Acceptance. They find the oppoſition of this boſom Enemy moſt ſenſible, when their intereſt, duty, and deſire is, to be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97664:29"/>moſt ſerious in ingaging their heart for God; when they are about to make the neareſt Approaches to Heaven; when they do ſo, or when they have juſt done ſo. This is one part of their <hi>Burden,</hi> which may well make them deſire a State of perfect Holineſs, and full Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Apprehenſion and Senſe of their <hi>Diſtance from Chriſt,</hi> while they are in the Body, is another reaſon why they thus Groan. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>now</hi> in us, the hope of Glory; but our injoyment of him is very imperfect in compariſon of what we expect: And if we have any true Love to Chriſt, we muſt needs deſire to be with him, to behold his Glory, to love him more, and feel the communications of his Love in a higher degree. If we know a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of the Sweetneſs of Communion with him, we muſt needs breath after ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler meaſures of it: And the ſenſe of our preſent diſtant ſtate, wherein we know ſo little of God and Chriſt, and love him leſs; wherein we continue to ſin againſt him, and daily ſmart under the bitter fruits of ſin, and dwell among thoſe who provoke and diſhonour him every day; may well
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97664:30"/>make us figh to be <hi>at home,</hi> that we may injoy that Preſence of Chriſt, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, which cannot be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained but by Dying. Do we not own it beſt, <hi>to be with Chriſt?</hi> the beſt Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the beſt Place, the beſt Condition and State, the beſt Enjoyments? Certainly the little we know of him, is enough to make us deſire to be with him; the little we have already received, may make us long to receive more.</p>
                  <p>Such will not ſay with the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> when the Prophet offered to ſpeak for her to the King; I am already at home;
<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>I dwell among my own People;</hi> I am pleaſed with my Station; I like my preſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode; I am not ambitious of any better; I care not for any other Life, or World, if I may but have this, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No, ſays a Holy Soul, I am a Stranger here on Earth, a Paſtenger, a Pilgrim through this World, <hi>as all my Fathers were;</hi> I ſeek another Country, an Heavenly one; I belong to another City that hath Foundations; My Principal Kindred, Relations and Friends are not here, but in that other Country. My Father is in Heaven, my Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is at his Right-hand in Glory, and the moſt of my Brethren are gone to him, and the reſt are haſtening as well
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97664:30"/>as I; My Heart and Hopes are there, I deſire to be one of them, I would be glad to make one of that great and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſembly of the <hi>Firſt-born,</hi> where is God the Judge of all, and the Bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, <hi>with an innumerable Company of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the Spirits of Juſt Men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect:</hi> Yea, I groan under this diſtance, and abſence from my deareſt Lord. Were it put to my Choice, I would venture up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any difficulties, and dangers, and deaths, rather than it ſhould continue: Nothing but the ſenſe of Duty to him, to ſerve the purpoſes of his glory here, can make me brook ſo long a ſeparation: otherwiſe, whatever the League be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and this Body, I had rather be with Chriſt, though that be diſſolved: If there be no way to come to Heaven but by Dying, I would rather dye to be there, than live in this abſence from Chriſt my Saviour; that I may doubt of his love no more, and feel no more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of his diſpleaſure; that he may hide his Face from me no more, but with ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Compaſſions receive and imbrace me. And what is there in Death, that I ſhould fear it, that is half ſo frightful and grievous as my Abſence from Chriſt? What is there in this earthly Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, or in this preſent World, that I ſhould
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97664:31"/>ſo love an abode in it, and not be willing to quit it, that I may be preſent with the Lord! O let him call me when he will, if he will receive my departing Soul! Let him draw me through the duſt of the Earth, if he will draw me nearer to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and bring me to his bleſſed Preſence. 'Tis <hi>there</hi> I long to be, 'tis that my heart is ſet upon, that is it I groan for; I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of his Preſence, <hi>to behold his Glory,</hi> and receive the Communications and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections of it. Henceforth I would not be unwilling and backward to go unto him, but rather ſay, <hi>O when ſhall I come and appear before him!</hi> But there is a fourth Particular to which I haſten.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nequal Communications</hi> of Light, and Grace, and Comfort from Chriſt, while in the Body, make them thus groan to be uncloth'd. There is not that ſteddineſs, and Conſtancy in ſuch Communications from God in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State, as hereafter there will be; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it ſuitable to the Character and Condition of Strangers, and Travellers, that there ſhould. Sometimes therefore we may have better Entertainment than at other times; we may not expect to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97664:31"/>have the ſame Sunſhine, and Fair wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, during our whole Pilgtimage. The Light of God's Countenance may be ſometimes cover'd, and overcaſt. The inward ſtate of things, between <hi>God</hi> and our <hi>Souls</hi> may be often alter'd. But, when we ſhall be at home in our Father's Houſe, in the preſence of our Lord, there will be a fulneſs of uninterrupted Joy, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Pleaſure. Chriſtians are now ſometimes in the Mount, and then again in the Valley: Sometimes they can Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, ſoon after they are Mourning and Dejected. Sometimes the Love of God is ſtrong and vigorous, ſoon after the Love of the World prevails again in ſome ſad Inſtance or other, to grieve the Holy Spirit of God, and cauſe him to withdraw. Sometimes they can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the Promiſes with Comfort, and go to God, with Holy Confidence, as to their Father, and think of Eternity, and another World, with tranſporting Joy, and of the Heavenly Inheritance as their own, with raiſed Deſires, and Delight; within a Day, or two, it may be, they are again plunged in the Mire, and ſunk into the depths of Darkneſs, and Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, ſo as not to be able to hold up their heads.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:97664:32"/>
                  <p> Sometimes at the Table of the Lord, they have Refreſhing Views of the Glory of Chriſt, in his Love and Grace, as bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Curſe which they deſerv'd; as manifeſting his ſpecial Kindneſs, and Sealing his Love, with particular Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to their Souls, as Intereſted in all the Benefits of his Meritorious Death; Hereby they are Reviv'd, and Quickned, and Strengthned, and enabled to ſay, <hi>I am as one who hath found favour in his ſight; My Beloved is mine, and I am his. He led me into his Banqueting-Houſe, his Banner o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me was Love.</hi> He called to me, as to the Unbelieving Diſciple, Come, <hi>reach hither thy hand, thruſt it into my ſide and heart,</hi> ſee how I have loved thee, Come, <hi>feel the print of the Spear, and of the Nails in my Hands and Feet;</hi> ſee what I ſuffer'd for thee, to expreſs my Love; What can I deny thee after this? Upon this an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulting Joy muſt needs enſue, but it did not laſt. And it may be the next Month they bewail that it is quite otherwiſe with 'em; Sometimes their hearts are enlarged, and delighted in Prayer, Thanſgiving, Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis their Joy ſometimes to go to the Houſe of God, and call upon his Name, and be employed in Heavenly Work, to Sing the High Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God in the Solemn Aſſemblies;</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:97664:32"/>
                  <p> But this is not conſtant, and equal; not always alike.</p>
                  <p>Could a Chriſtian Act Faith at all times, as ſometimes he is enabled to do; could he every day feel the Love of Chriſt, and expreſs his own, as ſometimes; could he always reſign, devote, yeild himſelf to the Lord, with that entire Adoration, Submiſſion, and Satisfaction in the divine Will, and Glory, Goodneſs, and Wiſdom, as ſometimes, and on ſome Occaſions; he would hardly believe himſelf a ſtranger, and Foreinner in this world, he would be tempted to take Earth for Heaven, and ſay <hi>tis Good to be here.</hi> But whatever Influences of Grace and Comfort we now receive, they are not ſteddy, equal, and conſtant; and tis but fit that we who are only Paſſengers through this World, and are not at home, ſhould be thus made ſenſible of our true Character and Condition, and not find the Way or Weather alike good, or our own Health equal, or our Accommodations, Proviſions and Entertainment here. This helps to make as long for a Better State and Life.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:97664:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Reſurrection of the Body. It is Poſſible. Probable, and Certain. Some have been raiſed from the Dead Where were their Souls during their Separation from their Bodies? Chriſt's Reſurrection of the Body farther il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated and proved.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>The Fourth thing propoſed is to prove, that this Bleſſed ſtate and Life, which Chriſtians deſire and long for, is not ſuch a one, wherein they are to be alway <hi>without a Body,</hi> but <hi>to have their Bodies rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, changed,</hi> and <hi>glorified,</hi> or <hi>to be cloathed upon with an Houſe from Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Poſſibility of the Reſurrection of the Body,</hi> the <hi>Probability,</hi> and the <hi>Certainty</hi> of it, have been often and largely
<note n="*" place="bottom">See Dr. <hi>Peirſon.</hi> Dr, Towerſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on the Creed. Art. XI. of the Reſurrection of the Body. And Mr. <hi>Baoeter</hi>'s Saints Reſt, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. and Self-denial, <hi>Chap.</hi> 38.</note> proved.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97664:33"/>That it is <hi>poſſible,</hi> both on the part of the <hi>Agent</hi> and <hi>Patient:</hi> Who, that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the <hi>Divine Omniſcience</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> can doubt, but that God can remake an Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Body of that Duſt, into which it is reſolved; and however it be diſperſed, find out, and rally the ſeveral parts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and unite them one to another? What Impoſſibility is it, that the deſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed parts of a Man's Body ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed into their due Scituation and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and reduced to a Temper, fit to diſcharge the Functions and Operations of Life? and that the Soul ſhould be Re-united to a Body thus Reſtored? How is it impoſſible? Or why ſhould it be Difficult to him, who did at firſt frame and temper this Body out of the Duſt, and inſpire a Reaſonable Soul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; and out of a meer Chaos make this Beautiful World? who formed and faſhioned our Bodies in the Womb; which is as ſtrange an inſtance of All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power, as the Reſurrection from the Dead will be: who gives us every Morning, and every Spring, a little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the Reſurrection of the Dead; Who makes <hi>the dry Bones to live, and is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf?</hi> Therefore to ſuch as doubt, or deny this, we muſt ſay as our Saviour to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97664:34"/>
                     <hi>Sadduces; You err, not knowing the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, nor the Power of God.</hi> Or, we may Expoſtulate, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 26.8</note> 
                     <hi>What? Doth it ſeem incredible to you, that God ſhould raiſe the Dead?</hi> Is there any Atome of our Duſt can eſcape his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, though cloathed with different forms and figures, and hath paſſed through various changes, ſwallowed by Beaſts, or conſumed by Fire, or ſcattered by the Wind? Doth not the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on remain, though it put on a variety of forms? May not the Subſtance be intire, notwithſtanding all the transforming alterations that can be ſuppoſed? The Divine Knowledge being infinite, and his Providence reaching to the leaſt, as well as to the greateſt parts of the World, to the beginning progreſs and diſſolution of every one, he may eaſily call forth every part, when the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time comes for the Re-union of Soul and Body. We muſt queſtion the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Omniſcience, as well as Power, if we doubt of this. And are there not many things in the firſt Creation, every whit as incredible, as the Collection of our ſcatter'd Duſt, and compacting theſe diſperſed Atomes into an Humane Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? Can it be harder to reſtore thoſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97664:34"/>things that were, than to create thoſe things that were not?
<note n="*" place="bottom">See Dr. <hi>Barrow's</hi> Works, 2 Vol. p. 520.</note> Is it more difficult to an Infinite Arm, to Allmighty and Invincible Power, to do this, than to make both Soul and Body at firſt? Is not the Bleſſed Redeemer, who hath all Power in Heaven and Earth, able to make good his Word, who is alſo the <hi>Amen, the faithful and true Witneſs?</hi> and therefore to deceive us with a Promiſe and Expectation, of what he cannot, or will not do, would be an eternal Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Truth, and Holineſs, and other Attributes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>God hath already raiſed Some from the Dead, whereof we have Inſtances both in the Old Teſtament, and in the New. Many were raiſed by <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and <hi>many of the Saints came out of their Graves at the Death of Chriſt, and went into the Holy City, and appeared publickly to many.</hi> If it be inquired, Where were the Souls of thoſe that were thus raiſed, during
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97664:35"/>the ſpace between their Death and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection? This being not to be known but by Revelation, and that ſpeaking nothing of it, we may ſafely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our Ignorance. It was a peculiar Caſe, that does not make a general Rule; and therefore our Inquiry about it muſt be very wary. It is ſufficient to ſay, they were in the hands of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were. What if there were a particular Diſpenſation in regard of them, different from the caſe of thoſe, who are not to be raiſed till the laſt day: Nothing can well be propoſed in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſuch a Queſtion, but what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectural.</p>
                  <p>Therefore rejecting all Suppoſitions that cannot be reconciled to other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Doctrines, and Articles of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, we may ſay,
<note n="*" place="bottom">Aeuures de Mr. <hi>Claude.</hi> Lettre 16.</note> That either they were received to <hi>Heaven,</hi> or remained in <hi>the Air,</hi> at a little diſtance from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; Or, they continued in <hi>the Body,</hi> which was to be quickly raiſed again, without animating and informing that Body. If we ſay the <hi>firſt,</hi> and that theſe Souls returned from Heaven to their Bodies again, for the Manifeſtation of the Glory of Chriſt in ſuch a Miracle;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97664:35"/>it is no more unſuitable and unbecoming an Holy Soul to be willing of this, and to be thus imployed, than was the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of the Son of God, for the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Father. If we ſay the <hi>Second,</hi> that they remained in the Air not far from the Body, it being but for a little while, What Inconvenience, or ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence can be aſſigned of ſuch a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition? If we rather chuſe the <hi>Third</hi> way of ſolving this, it is conſiderable what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Euti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> whom he raiſed from the
<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 20.10.</note> Dead; <hi>Be not troubled, for his Life, his Soul is in him,</hi> though it did not then animate, and inform his Body. As to thoſe who were raiſed at the time of Chriſt's death it was only for a little while, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Teſtimony to our Lord, and then they laid down their Bodies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and returned to the Reſt and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of departed Souls.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>But, <hi>The Reſurrection of our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> is the great thing here to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as an Argument both of the Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and Certainty of our Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97664:36"/>For thus the Apoſtle Argues at large, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 12. If it be Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Proved, and Aſſured to us, that Chriſt is Riſen, <hi>How is it that ſome ſay, There is no Reſurrection of the Dead?</hi> that is, How can any deny the poſſibility of it, when there is ſuch an Evidence and Proof? How can it be doubted, but that the ſame Power which raiſed Chriſt from the dead, can alſo quicken our mortal Bodies? when <hi>the exceeding great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his mighty power, was diſplayed in
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Eph. 19.20.</note> raiſing Chriſt from the dead?</hi> His Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection aſſures us, that his Death and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice were Satisfactory to the Juſtice of God: and all the Promiſes that concern the Bleſſings of the eyerlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the ſure Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>David,</hi> are hereby confirmed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 32, 33, 34. <hi>We declare unto you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> how that the Promiſe which was made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, God hath fulfilled the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> unto us their Children, in that he hath raiſed up Jeſus again; as it is alſo written <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Pſalm, Thou art my Son, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> day have I begotten thee. And, as con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                           <desc>•••••</desc>
                        </gap>ng that he raiſed him up from the dead, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> no more to return to corruption; he ſaid on this wiſe, I will give you the ſure Mercies of</hi> David. And therefore, after his Reſurrection, he
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97664:36"/>ſaluted his Diſciples with <hi>Peace, John</hi> 20.21. And God, as <hi>the God of peace,</hi> is ſaid to raiſe Chriſt from the Dead: For, had he not been reconciled, he would have left him in the Grave. Now both the <hi>Moral,</hi> and the <hi>Natural</hi> Impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Reſurrection is removed by the <hi>Death,</hi> and the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of Chriſt; The former by the Merit of his Death, and the latter by his Reſurrection: for he can do the ſame for all Believers. If his Power be not ſufficient to raiſe us, it could not be ſufficient to raiſe him. He is now a
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.45.</note> 
                     <hi>Quickening Spirit,</hi> able to give Life, as the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Death to his Poſterity. And he was raiſed as a <hi>publick perſon,</hi> and the Head of his Church.</p>
                  <p>Our Perſons are redeemed by Chriſt, as conſiſting of Soul and Body; and our Bodies Sanctified by him, and are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall be raiſed by him. Yea, we are ſaid to <hi>riſe with him,</hi> and to be <hi>ſet down in heavenly places, in,</hi> and <hi>with him.</hi> It is not more true that he died for our ſins, than that be roſe again for our <hi>Justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and if for <hi>that,</hi> he roſe for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection too: For the guilt of ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing removed, which is the meritorious
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97664:37"/>cauſe of Death; <hi>Death,</hi> which is the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, ſhall not remain, but be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in Victory; whereas it lives, and reigns, and keeps the Field, till the Reſtirrection. But we are aſſured that <hi>The Sea, and Death, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Grave ſhall give up their Dead,</hi> Rev. 20.13. And then not only the ſting of Death, but Death it ſelf ſhall dye, and ceaſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: for <hi>there ſhall be no more death,</hi> Rev. 21.4. Our dead Bodies ſhall then live, ſo as to dye no more. For, <hi>if we believe on him that raiſed Chriſt from the dead, the ſame Spirit, that raiſed Chriſt, ſhall be the Author of our Reſurrection,</hi> Rom. 8.23. And, <hi>if we believe that Jeſus dyed and roſe again, even them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus, will God bring with him,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. He that was dead is now alive, and behold he lives for evermore; and <hi>he hath the keys of Death and Hell,</hi> Rev. 1.18. And he has expreſly told us, that the hour is coming, in the which <hi>All that are in their graves ſhall hear his voice, and ſhall come forth, They that have done good unto the Reſurrection of Life, and they that have done evil, unto the Reſurrection of Damnation,</hi> John 5.28.29. And this is the will of God that ſent him, that every one who believeth on him, ſhall have everlaſting Life; and <hi>he will raiſe him up at the laſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97664:37"/>day,</hi> John 6.40. The like he declares afterwards to <hi>Martha, I am the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and the Life, he that believeth in me, tho he were dead yet ſhall he live,</hi> John 11.25. He is the Firſt born from the dead, and Believers are <hi>the Children of the Reſurrection,</hi> Coloſ. 1.18. His Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection not only proves the poſſibility of ours, but it is the pledge of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. <hi>God having raiſed him up, hath looſed the pains of Death, ſince it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible he ſhould be holden by them;</hi> Natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impoſſible, becauſe of his Divine Power; and legally impoſſible, becauſe Divine Juſtice, after ſuch a Satisfaction as the Death of Chriſt, required that he ſhould be raiſed to Life, and receive a Diſcharge and Reward.</p>
                  <p>We could hardly believe the Dead ſhould riſe to Life, if Chriſt by his own Reſurrection, and by raiſing others, had not proved it poſſible, and already done. But he hath not conquer'd Death for himſelf alone, but for his Members too, and to them he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, that they ſhall
<note n="*" place="margin">John 11.26.</note> 
                     <hi>never ſee Death,</hi> or come within the Proſpect or Danger of it: And not only ſhall not, but <hi>cannot dye any more,</hi> after the Reſurrection, for they <hi>ſhall be equal to the Angels,</hi> Luke 20.36.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97664:38"/>His Victory over Death was declared by his Reſurrection, and his entrance into Glory did Compleat the Conqueſt. Now as Chriſt hath carried his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature into Heaven, we are to be made like him, and bear the Image of the Heavenly <hi>Adam,</hi> and therefore our Fleſh ſhall be raiſed too. <hi>He is the firſt-fruits of them that ſleep,</hi> 1 Cor. 15, 20. And, it is
<note n="*" place="bottom">Biſhop <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher.</hi>
                     </note> obſervable, tha the Roſe from the Dead on that Day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Jews</hi> obſerve their <hi>Feaſt of Firſt-fruits.</hi> That Feaſt was not ſtinted to any day of the Month, as other Feaſts were, but was to be always on the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row after the Paſſover Sabbath, that ſo it might fall always on the Firſt day of the Week, the Day of Chriſt's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. Well therefore might the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>Chriſt being Riſen, is become the Firſt-fruits of them that ſleep;</hi> As the Offering of the Firſt-fruits amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> Conſecrated all the reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:97664:38"/>
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>Neither can we ſuppoſe our Happineſs would be compleat, without the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Body. As Soul and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy concur to the Conſtitution of man, the Soul is in a State of widowhood till reunited to the Body. And in this Life the Body has a ſhare in the work and ſervice of the <hi>Man,</hi> which is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded or puniſhed, as executing the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Soul. And the members of the Body ſerve as <hi>members of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or <hi>Sin.</hi> The Law of God commands the intire Man, compoſed of Soul and Body, and this Law is obeyed or violated by both, though the moral good or evil of our Actions be chiefly attributed to the Soul, as the principal Agent; But on this Account the Body ſhall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in the rewards or Puniſhment of the next Life, if the intire Perſon be to be recompenced. And it is with reſpect to the Body, that ſeemed to be loſt, that the Reſurrection is promiſed; the Body reſolved into duſt, or ſwallowed in the Sea, or conſumed by fire: Such promiſes of the Reſurrection are made to Believers for their encouragment and hope. Beſides, there are many Objects
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97664:39"/>in the heavenly State that do ſuppoſe a Body, and are to be diſcerned by our bodily ſenſes, as, the glorious beauty and magnificence of the bleſſed manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Humane Nature of our glorious Redeemer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On which, and many other accounts, the Body ſhall be raiſed, and changed, and glorified.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p>Reaſon it ſelf would make this <hi>Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> Man being created with a Body and a Soul, which have ſo natural an Inclination to one another, that there is an appetite and deſire, as it ſeems, to be united, and co-operate together, and many of our Capacities, of Joy and Comfort, as well as of Sorrow and Grief, reſult from, and depend upon this Union: In order therefore to the full and final Felicity that God will confer on ſome, and for the greater Miſery wherewith divine Juſtice will puniſh others, it is very probable from principles of Reaſon, that God will raiſe the Bodys of men; That being united to their Souls, they may be better capable of enjoying the promiſed Happineſs, or ſuffering the threatened miſery of the next World. This ſeems
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97664:39"/>to be the ſenſe of <hi>Job</hi> 14. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. ver. where he ſays, that <hi>all the days of his appointed time, I will wait till my change come,</hi> Speaking of <hi>the Reſurrection of the Body.</hi> There is hope of a Tree he ſaith, if it be cut down, that it will ſprout again; but man dyeth, and where is he? he lyeth down, and riſeth not, till the Heavens be no more. <hi>If a man dye, ſhall he live again? All the days of my appointed Time &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> of Bleſſedneſs. <hi>p.</hi> 210.</note> According to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Apprehenſion, and Appearance, the State of man at death is hopeleſs; But he profeſſeth his Expectation, that at a <hi>ſet</hi> and <hi>appointed Time,</hi> God would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him, ſo as to recall him out of the Grave: And therefore puts the queſtion, <hi>If a man dye, ſhall he live again?</hi> And till the appointed time when God ſhould revive him, out of the duſt, he would wait for that glorious Change. when <hi>God ſhall have a deſire to the work of his hands,</hi> i. e. not allways forget to reſtore and perfect his own Creature.</p>
                  <p>There are many Images and Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances of this. As in the Corn by which we live, when it is caſt on the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97664:40"/>earth, and buried in the ground, that it may corrupt; after it is corrupted, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives and multiplies: Our Bodys are fed with this conſtant Experiment. And the Apoſtles ſimilitude of a grain of Corn Sown in the ground, that it riſeth multiplied, augmented, and adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſets out the advantagious difference between the Qualities of our Bodys when they dye, and when they ſhall be raiſed. And herein he imitates the manner of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were wont familiariy to illuſtrate the buſineſs of the Reſurrection, by the ſimilitude of leed ſown in the ground, and ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up again. And what can we diſcern in a ſmall corn, or litle ſeed, of a Tree, with Body, Bark, Branches, Leaves, Flowers, Fruit? and yet afterwards we behold them, when the ſeed hath been ſown in the ground. The Apoſtle at large Inſiſts on this ſimilitude of <hi>ſeed,</hi> to explain the manner of the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.35. <hi>So</hi> alſo <hi>is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>Scot</hi> of the Chriſtian Liſe, <hi>part</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 7.</note>, So is this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Body to be the <hi>ſeed,</hi> and material Principle of our Reſurrection: For <hi>that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97664:40"/>which is ſown is not quickened, except it dye.</hi> And <hi>ſo</hi> is this Seed of our mortal Body to dye, and be corrupted, before it ſhall be raiſed again. And <hi>So</hi>is this dead corrupted Body to be raiſed and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened by the power of God. For <hi>God gives to every Seed a Body as it pleaſes him.</hi> And <hi>ſo</hi> are our dead Bodys to be raiſed again, into the proper form and kind of humane Bodys, for unto every ſeed God giveth <hi>his own Body.</hi> And, <hi>Lastly, So is the Reſurrection of the Dead;</hi> that is, <hi>So</hi> are thoſe humane Bodys to be changed, and altered by the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, as that which is but bare Seed when it is ſown; when it is quickened, it ſprings up into a long ſtalk and ear: <hi>So</hi> the raiſed Body ſhall be changed for the better.</p>
                  <p>This is further Illuſtrated by
<note n="*" place="bottom">Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> of Self-denial, <hi>p.</hi> 206.</note> another, That the dead Body of a man may be ſuppoſed to have a living Root, as truely as the plants in winter. The Soul is the Root of the Body, and the Soul is ſtill alive; And Chriſt is the Root of the Soul, and he is ſtill alive: For though we are dead, <hi>our Life is hid
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97664:41"/>with Chriſt in God; and when he who is our Life ſhall appear,</hi> at the Spring of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, <hi>we ſhall alſo appear with him in Glory,</hi> Coloſ. 3.3, 4. There is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Union between Soul and Body, and a deep rooted Love of the Soul to its Body, and Inclination to it; ſo that it is mindful of it, and waits with long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for that hour when the Command of God, ſhall ſend it to revive that Body. Why may not the Living Soul, that is the Root and Life of the Body in the duſt, be the Inſtrument of God, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form its own Body, as it will be the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple that ſhall re-inform it? The Body in the Grave hath its own Relation to Chriſt, who is ſtill Living, and reſolved and ingaged by Promiſe, and inclined by Love to revive that Body. And when the Hour comes for this Soul that waits to be ſent again into the Body, what can hinder? The very Love of the Soul to its Body, and its deſire to be re-united, is a kind of Natural Cauſe of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. A Candle not lighted, is as far from Light, and as much without it, as a dead body is without Life; and yet one touch of a lighted Candle will light that which never was lighted before: And ſo may one touch of the living Soul, that is now with Chriſt, put Life into the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97664:41"/>body, that lies in the duſt. And as the lighted Candle makes the other like it, and Communicates of its Nature to it; ſo does the glorified Soul Communicate a new kind of Excellency to the Body, which it never had before; even to be a Spiritual, Glorious, Incorruptible, and Immortal Body. And God takes the Soul to Heaven before hand, that it may be firſt Glorified, and ſo be fit to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Glory to the body. So that there is more reaſon for the Reſurrection of the body, though it be turned to Earth; than there is reaſon that a Candle, that is gone out, ſhould be lighted again by another; or than there is reaſon, that I ſhould put on my Cloaths in the Morning which I put off at Night: For Nature diſpoſeth me to abhor nakedneſs, and deſire my Cloaths, and therefore in the Morning I will put them on: So Nature teaches the Seperated Soul to deſire a re-union with its body: And therefore when the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection-Morning comes, it will glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take the word from Chriſt, and give that vital touch to the body, that ſhall revive it; and ſo put on its antient Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but wonderfully changed for the better, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:97664:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>That the Same Body, for Substance, is to be Raiſed again at the laſt day. And what the Change will be of theſe Bodies hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, from what they now are.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>IF it be inquired, How can <hi>the ſame Body,</hi> after ſo many Changes, be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and re-united to the Soul? And what need is there of Aſſcrting, That it ſhall be <hi>the ſame?</hi> It ought to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, that the very word <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> doth ſuppoſe, or imply this, That the Bodies of Men ſhall hereafter be truly <hi>the ſame</hi> with thoſe that died. It is the Body falls to the ground, when the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit goes upward; That Body that then fell, is to be raiſed again, and no other Body than that. <hi>This</hi> Mortal Body ſhall be quickened by the Spirit of Chriſt, that <hi>now</hi> falls, to the ground: The ſame Fleſh that was ſeparated from the Soul at death, ſhall be united to it again: The ſame Temple that was deſtroyed, ſhall be re-built; The ſame Tabernacle that was diſſolved, ſhall be raiſed. We are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97664:42"/>bid to fear God, who can deſtroy <hi>Soul and Body in Hell,</hi> Mat. 10.28. What cauſe of fear, if <hi>this</hi> very body be not to be raiſed?
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Reſurgere non eſt niſi ejus quod cecidit.</hi> Tert. adverſ. Marc. l. 5. c. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>This Corruptible muſt put on Incorruption, this Mortal put on Immertality:</hi> As the <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt, which is our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar, with which he roſe, was the ſame that he depoſited in the Grave; and as the bodies of thoſe whom our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour raiſed, when he was on Earth, were the ſame with thoſe in which they died. And how ſhall the Graves, and Sea give up their Dead at the Laſt Day, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.13. What need of this, if the ſame Bodies are not to be raiſed? for they can give up no other Bodies than what they received. Theſe Recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Dead, might be ſuffered to be quiet for ever, and the Bodies that reſt there to remain there for ever, if we do not expect the ſame Body to be raiſed.</p>
                  <p>And as the Body was the Servant of
<note place="bottom">Photii Bibliotheca. <hi>S. Nilt Oratio, Prima &amp; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda in Patch.</hi> p. 1528, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97664:43"/>the Soul, in good or evil actions,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Si quidem Sola Anima praeclaras edidit Officii Actiones Jola eriam Coronetur. Sin autem Corpus quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que partem ſuſtinuerit Certaminum, coronetur etiam A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima unà cum ipſo Corpore. Hoc enim juſtum, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum, &amp; Convenicntiſſimum eſt.</hi> Iſid. Peluſ. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. Epiſt. 201.</note> He that did good or evil in one Body, is not to be Rewarded or Puniſhed in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for that other Body would not be a part of the whole. Our preſent bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are the Members of Chriſt, and the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, and he will not ſuffer them Eternally to be loſt. What words can more plainly expreſs, that it is <hi>the ſame body for ſubſtance,</hi> than the putting on of Incorruption, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality; declaring, that the Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, Mortal Body, that is laid in the Grave, is that which ſhall be Immortal and Incorruptible?</p>
                  <p>This has been the common opinion of Chriſtians in all Ages. Upon this account the Primitive Chriſtians were ſo careful of the Bodies of their decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Friends, manifeſting their belief, that their Souls ſhould meet theſe Bodies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. On this account their <hi>Pagan</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, to ſhow their ſpite and malice, when they had burnt their bodies to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97664:43"/>aſhes, ſcattered their duſt in the Air, or had thrown them into Rivers; that, if it were poſſible, they might deprive them of all hopes of a <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and make it impoſſible; Some of them tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph'd, ſaying, <hi>Now let us ſee whether they can riſe again, whether their God can help them, or deliver them out of our
<note n="*" place="bottom">See more of this in Dr. <hi>More</hi>'s <hi>Myſtery of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> l. 6. c. 4. With Dr. <hi>Beaumont</hi>'s Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereon; And Dr. <hi>Bury</hi>'s <hi>Naked Goſpel,</hi> Part. 1. Chap. 11. With Mr. <hi>Nichols</hi>'s Anſwer.</note> hands.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>But though the bodies ſhall then, for <hi>Subſtance,</hi> be <hi>the ſame,</hi> with thoſe we now have, yet the modes and qualities of them will be ſo altered, that they will be quite another kind of bodies, than thoſe we have for the preſent. In refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to this Expected Change, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith in this Chapter, ver. 7. <hi>That we walk by Faith, not by Sight.</hi> We do not yet know what our Happy State, by that Change, will be; but in another place he doth more particularly ſpeak of it, and more diſtinctly, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42, 43, 44.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:97664:44"/> 1. That our vile bodies, <hi>Sown in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, ſhall be Raiſed in Glory;</hi> ſhall be made <hi>Glorious, like the Glorious Body of Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3.21. <hi>That which is ſown in diſhonour, ſhall be raiſed in Glory, and bear the Image of the Heavenly</hi> Adam: Shall be like the <hi>Glorious Body of Chriſt</hi> in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Parts, even in External form and figure, and it may be ſtature too. But, for certain, how vile and mean ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the matter of theſe bodies now be, however they may corrupt and putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie in the Grave, they ſhall come forth in a bright and beautiful form; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to which, the moſt Exquiſite Beauty is but Darkneſs and Deformity. <hi>For the Righteous ſhall ſhine as the Sun, in the Firmament of their Father,</hi> Matth. 13.43. As the Stars of Heaven differ from a Clod of Earth, or a Carrion in the Ditch, ſo will their Glorified Bodies from this Earthly Houſe. The very activity, ſprightfulneſs, and joy of their Glorified Souls, will make their faces ſhine, and give the Countenance an amiable Air. Yea, <hi>Solomen, in all his Glory, was not arrayed like one of theſe</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Reſurrection, glittering with Heavenly brightneſs, and deck'd with Light, as with a Garment. The beams of Chriſt's Glory, who is the Sun of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97664:44"/>Righteouſneſs, ſhall reflect a Luſtre up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, beſides what ſhall be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from their Glorified Souls.</p>
                  <p>Our Lord gave a Specimen of this at his <hi>Transfiguration,</hi> and his Glorified Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is to be the Pattern of ours; His face did then ſhine as the Sun, <hi>Matt.</hi> 17.2. the Subſtance remaining, there was a Glorious Appearance: For he had the ſame Lineaments in <hi>Tabor,</hi> as at the foot of the <hi>Mount;</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Peter</hi> could not have diſtinguiſhed him from <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Elias.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Mr. <hi>Charnock,</hi> of <hi>Christ's Exaltation,</hi> Vol. 2. P. 1093.</note> But his Body now in Heaven doth more excel in Glory that Body he had on Earth, than the Glory of the Sun ſurpaſſes that of a Glow-worm; not only from the Glory of his Soul, but of his Divinity ſhining through it. What a wonderful Change muſt paſs on the bodies of the Glorified Saints, to make them capable of beholding this Glory of Chriſt; when a little Glimpſe of it on Mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> was more than a Mortal Eye could bear; it caſt <hi>Peter</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Exſtaſie? Our Lord forbad his Diſciples to ſpeak of the Glory of his <hi>Transfiguration,</hi> till after he was Riſen
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97664:45"/>from the Dead; but now is willing, and hath commanded it ſhould be ſpoken of, all the World over, that our thoughts and apprehenſions may be raiſed, to conſider that Glory, which this did but imperfectly ſhadow and repreſent. For if before his Reſurrection, and Aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Human Nature of Chriſt had ſuch a Glory, how much more in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? and we ſhall be like him. <hi>Moſes</hi> on the Mount did ſo ſhine, that the People were afraid to come near him, and he was forced to caſt a Vail upon his Face. One ray of Chriſts Glory on the Holy Martyr <hi>Stephen,</hi> made his Countenance ſhine with an Angelical Luſtre. And <hi>when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him;</hi> he will then be admired of all them that believe: We ſhall be like him who is the Bleſſed and only Potentate, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, who alone hath Immortality, dwelling in that Light which no man can approach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; whom no man hath ſeen, or can ſee, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 6.15, 16.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There will be a change of theſe bodies in reſpect of <hi>Spirituality.</hi> It is ſown a Natural body, and raiſed a <hi>Spiritual one.</hi> The groſſneſs and Feculency that now adheres to it, ſhall be purged off. Not Spiritual in oppoſition to <hi>Corporeal,</hi>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:97664:45"/>that is a Contradiction; but in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Natural;</hi> of a Spiritual Nature in oppoſition to this infirm fleſh; a body raiſed to the higheſt degree of Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as near the Angelical State as a body can be brought. It is called our Houſe, <hi>from Heaven,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not an Houſe that is to deſcend from Heaven to us, but that is of an <hi>Heavenly Nature,</hi> all of a Peice with Heaven. So Purified, as to be Aſſimilated to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Region, where we are to dwell for ever. <hi>The first Man was of the Earth, Earthly; the ſecond Man is the Lord from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> And from each of them we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of an anſwerable Nature. <hi>As is the Earthly, ſuch are they that are Earthly,</hi> even all of us in our fleſhly State having earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodies from an earthly <hi>Adam,</hi> and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural bodies from the natural <hi>Adam.</hi> And <hi>as is the Henvenly, ſuch are they that are Heavenly:</hi> For Chriſt will make them like himſelf; and as he hath an Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spiritual body, and not an Earthly. Natural body, ſo ſhall his Members have, that they may be like him. And as we have born the Image of the Earthly, in having a Natural Fleſhly body, we ſhall alſo bear the Image of the Heavenly <hi>Adam,</hi> in having a <hi>Spiritual Body,</hi> not needing the uſe of Meats, or Drinks,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97664:46"/>or any of the refreſhments or pleaſures of the animal Life, or be imployed in any of thoſe Acts, whereby the body is now denominated <hi>Natural,</hi> and ſuited to this Earthly State. But our bodies ſhall then be <hi>Spiritual,</hi> ſuited to the Life that Angels and Saints live in Heaven; every way greatly refined, and the Activity of our Spirits improved, without the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and infirmities of fleſh and blood; ſhall be inveſted with Caeleſtial Qualities, depending wholly on the Soul, and yielding ready obedience, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to its deſires and motions, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting all its Commands with pleaſure and Diſpatch. Yea, the imployment and operations of the body ſhall be raiſed above thoſe in the preſent ſtate, as much as the Imployment of a King exceeds that of a Scullion. This Spiritual Body one repreſents by <hi>Organized Light,</hi> as a torch or wood that looſeth its droſſy and foggy qualities, when heightened into a pure flame, or minerals heightened into Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Bodies of the Saints ſhall be changed from weak and paſſive, into <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Powerful Bodies.</hi> Sown in <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> but raiſed in <hi>Power.</hi> They are now dull and ſluggiſh, but then they ſhall be nimble and active, like the Body
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97664:46"/>of Chriſt, that, at his Aſcenſion into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, being done in one day, moved many thouſands of Miles in an hour; the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance between the higheſt Heavens and this Earth, being computed to be ſome hundred millions of Miles: They ſhall be raiſed with Angelical Agility and Strength: He that is weak among them ſhall be as <hi>David;</hi> he that is as <hi>David,</hi> ſhall be as <hi>an Angel of God;</hi> moving without difficulty, and without wearineſs. Now we often find the <hi>Body</hi> cannot keep Peace with the Soul, the Fleſh is weak when the Spirit is willing, but it ſhall be raiſed in <hi>Power.</hi> It is now liable to Diſeaſes and Paſſions, can do little and ſuffers much; but no Diſeaſes or Infirmities ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after hinder its motions, or impair its Health. A glorified Body will move without wearineſs, and faſt without hunger, and wake for ever without need of refreſhment: Herein there will be a ſuitableneſs to the Activity of a glorified Soul; and without this they could not bear the weight of the Heavenly Glory: Beſides, they are to indure to all Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without reparation by meat, and drink, and fleep.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. They ſhall be <hi>Incorruptible,</hi> and <hi>Immortal.</hi> It is ſown in Corruption, it is raiſed in Incorruption. This mortal
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97664:47"/>ſhall put on Immortality, They ſhall dye no more, but live for ever. Therefore the day of the Reſurrection, is called <hi>the Redemption of our Bodies;</hi> They ſhall not be liable to be put out of tune by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, and pains, and numberleſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, as now; which often make Life it ſelfe a Burden. They ſhall be Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, without needing that Labour by day, or ſleep by night, which now we beſtow to ſupply their Neceſſities, and repair their decays, and prevent Death. Now the Body has the ſeeds of Mortality and Corruption, but ſhall then be refined from all ſuch Principles; There ſhall not be a tendency to Death, in the nature and conſtitution of the Body; ſuch will be the glorious Change, that they <hi>cannot dye any more,</hi> 20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 36. They that were raiſed by Chriſt when on Earth, they dyed again, their <hi>ſecond Life</hi> was no more exempt from death, than their <hi>Firſt:</hi> But at the Reſurrection, <hi>Mortality ſhall be ſwallowed up of Life,</hi> it ſhall loſe its power and force for ever.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:97664:47"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Inferences of Truth, and Duty from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Diſcourſe. The Soul doth not periſh, when the Body dies. The Felicity of the Soul is what we principally deſire. Our Faith ſhould be conſirmed in the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Expectation of this Glorious Change. Our affections and Converſation ſhould be Suitable</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let us not then imagin the State of the Dead to be a State of <hi>Non-exiſtence,</hi> or Annihilation, that the Soul periſhes with the Body, and that we are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Hope of its Reſurection. Whereas, when our Soul paſſes into a ſtate of Reſt and Joy with Chriſt, our Fleſh reſts in Hope that theſe Bodys ſhall be raiſed and reunited to their glorious Souls. We are to paſs through the Valley of Death to a Bleſſed Life. This is the Deſire and Hope of all the Followers of Chriſt. <hi>And theſe very Deſires of a bleſſed Life beyond the Grave, will prove the Certainty of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:97664:48"/>
                  <p> We muſt have ſtrange Thoughts of the infinitely wiſe and holy God, and of his Love and Goodneſs, to imagin he ſhould give his Creatures ſuch a Knowledge of himſelf that makes them deſire more, even a Deſire to know, and love, and injoy him perpetually, and yet never intend an eternal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of himſelf, anſwerable to thoſe Deſires. Can we think the bleſſed God would deceive and mock thoſe that deſire to ſeek, and pleaſe him? by inabling them to aſpire after a Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in his preſence, and by giving them a Capacity for it, And then to fruſtrate and diſappoint his own work? Can we think, that God would excite their Deſires after another, and a better ſtate, and yet never admit them to it? Can we imagin that God would raiſe their Deſires from ſin and this World, to himſelf and Heaven, and that theſe ſhall never be anſwered in a happy Iſſue? Shall the very Sanctification of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture prepare for our Torment, and help to make us miſerable? Will the God of Love and Grace inable us by his Grace to hunger and thirſt after Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and after the bleſſed viſion of his Face in Glory, and yet never deſign our Satisfaction?</p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:97664:48"/>
                  <p> The more any partake of the divine Image, we find that they groan and long the more earneſtly after another ſort of Happineſs, than is here to be had; after another State, and Life than now they enjoy: And may we not conclude that ſuch a State there is? The natural Deſire of Happineſs in all mankind, will do much to prove that there is ſuch a thing: But the holy Deſires of the Sanctified, influenced by the ſpirit of Grace, will much more prove it: That ſpirit of Chriſt, that hath inabled thee to long and pray for a more perfect State, that has conquered thy vain Deſires after earthly things, and raiſed them to ſeek the Knowledge, and Love, and Fruition of God; That Spirit is the Witneſs of Chriſt in thy Soul, that there is ſuch a State after Death, and that thou ſhalt ſhare in the Bleſſedneſs of it. He hath framed, and wrought, and fitted, and made thee meet for it. Theſe Deſires, it is true, are but faint and weak, to what the promiſed ſalvation may Juſtly cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge; yet they are holy and ſincere, and have God, and Chriſt, and his bleſſed Preſence above, for their Object; thou haſt his Image and ſeal imprinted on thy Nature, Mind and Will. This Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Experience in thy ſelf ſhall no be deſeated in its Tendency and Deſignt</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:97664:49"/>
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> In our Contemplation of this happy State, which the ſaints deſire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Grave, we ought to remember, that though the Glorious Change of the <hi>Body</hi> be <hi>one</hi> part, the Felicity of the <hi>Soul</hi> is the <hi>principal</hi> one: Yea the Glory of departed Souls, is one great Cauſe and Means of that happy Change, which we expect for the Body. To be with Chriſt, and behold his Glory, and partake of it, does eſpecially refer to the Soul: We ſhall <hi>ſee him as he is,</hi> and in that reſpect be made like him. We are now the Children of God by free Grace and Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but his admirable Love will not deſiſt, till our Conſormity to his Image be more compleat, till we are brought to his Preſence, and partake of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs to that degree, as to be the objects of his eternal Complacence and Delight. <hi>Father, I will,</hi> ſays Chriſt, <hi>that thoſe that thou haſt given me, ſhould be with me to behold my Glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then all our Sins and Failings, all our Follies and Infirmities, all our Wrinkles and Blemiſhes, all our Tranſgreſſions and Imperfections, ſhall be done away; and our Souls ſhall be waſhed white in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97664:49"/>the Blood of the Lamb, being conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to our Divine Pattern.</p>
                  <p>The leſſer Manifeſtations of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Glory of Chriſt, which we have ſometimes here, are highly valuable to a Saint, but unſpeakably ſhort of that which we expect; theſe hereafter will be more clear, more transforming, more ſatisfactory, and more laſting: We now ſee through a Glaſs, but darkly; but we ſhall know as we are known, for we ſhall ſee him as he is. We hope for an inlightened, and inlarged Mind to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Excellency and Radiancy of the Divine Perfections, ſhining in and through our glorified Redeemer. This will oblige the moſt Improved Saint that ever left this Earth, to cry out with the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> concerning <hi>Solomon,</hi> that the one half was never told them, was not known or believed before. And if we are changed into his Image by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding his Glory in the Goſpel-glaſs, the Viſion hereafter will be more clear; and ſo the Change will be greater, and the Delight and Complacence reſulting from it, muſt needs be unſpeakably more. And this is our Comfort, that it will be ſuch, as ſhall laſt <hi>for ever.</hi> If we have any Glymps of him at preſent by the Light of Faith, we quickly loſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97664:50"/>the ſight again: How ſoon does an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Cloud hide him from us? But the Felicity of the Bleſſed Viſion above, will be permanent, we ſhall dwell for ever in the joyful Light of his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and abide with him continually in the Heavenly Manſions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let us then indeavour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm our <hi>Faith</hi> in the Expectation of this bleſſed State, for Soul and Body after Death. Let us keep the Grounds of Faith viſible in our Eye; let us imploy our Thoughts frequently, and ſeriouſly upon the bleſſed Object: Let us deeply and often conſider the cogent Reaſons, upon which we believe and expect ſuch things; both the intrinſick Grounds of Faith, and the Motives of Credibility; that our Aſſent may be the more firm and laſting; that our Chriſtian Faith may influence us, as preſent things are wont to do.</p>
                  <p>Did we not look upon the great things of the other Life as <hi>uncertain</hi> we could not but reckon them preferable to the beſt of our preſent Injoyments. Did we believe them, we could not but deſire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> for our not
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97664:50"/>deſiring that bleſſed State, but our cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal <hi>Infidelity,</hi> that we believe it not: For were we but fully perſwaded of the truth of the Promiſes, we muſt needs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them for their Goodneſs, and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency; and then we ſhould long till Death did draw aſide the Vail, open the Gate of Heaven, and bring us into the Divine Preſence. But we waver and doubt concerning the inviſible future World; and hence it is that we cloſe with what is <hi>Preſent,</hi> becauſe we are not equally perſwaded of the Truth and Cortainty of what is <hi>Future.</hi> Let us then indeavour to ſtrengthen, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm our Faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Let us regulate our Affections and Carriage in this Earthly Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, as Perſons who believe and expect ſuch a glorious Change. Let us paſs the time of our Sojourning in this World, as <hi>Pilgrims and Strangers.</hi> Let us abſtain from fleſhly Luſts that War againſt our Souls. Let us uſe both our Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies anſwerable to the belief of ſuch things. Let us watch leſt we are ſurpriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into ſin by our bodily Senſes, Appetites and Imagination. Let us remember that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97664:51"/>the Soul and Body; like two diſeaſed Creatures bound together in one chain, do now mutually infect, corrupt, and Poyſon one another; Let us take heed of ſin by the inordinate Love of <hi>Bodily Pleaſure,</hi> or the undue fear of <hi>Bodily Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us imitate the Pattern of Chriſt while he dwelt in a Body, and labour to have the ſame Mind which he had, to be in this World as he was in it. Lot the good and evil of this World have leſs powerful impreſſion upon us. Let us not be over fond of the Pleaſures of the Animal Life; may they every day be leſs conſiderable with us! Let us not ſo love the <hi>Body,</hi> as on that account to decline any <hi>preſent Duty;</hi> much leſs ſo over-love it, as to prefer the Comforts of the preſent Life to a future Felicity.</p>
                  <p>Let us not regret over much that ſuch an earthly Tabernacle muſt fall into duſt, that ſuch a periſhing Body muſt diſſolve, and lye in the Grave. We are ſenſible how weak and uſeleſs it was for a good while at firſt, before the <hi>Body</hi> was fitted for the ſervice of the <hi>Soul;</hi> and we cannot but be ſenſible what a Trouble and Temptation it has been ſince: Let the burdens and inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the bodily Life be more tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97664:51"/>let us not be impatient under them; let us be willing that the outward Man decay, ſo that the inward Man be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, let our Judgment and Eſteem, our Deſires and Indeavours, our Joys and Sorrows, be rectified and moderated, as to all that refers to the <hi>Body,</hi> and this <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Life.</hi> Let our Eyes and Hearts be fixed on the Heavenly State, let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member we are a ſort of Creatures rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the other World, though we dwell at preſent in an earthly Tabernacle.</p>
                  <p>In the midſt of our earthly Comforts, let us think of the Heavenly State and Liſe as infinitely better. Let us keep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live the Deſires of the Preſence of Chriſt, and fuller Conformity to him, in the height of our Temporal Proſperity. Let the believing Thoughts of the Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial State be unſpeakably ſweeter to us, than the beſt of all this World, when it is moſt pleaſant, commodious, and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: Our Spirits are Diſtempered, and out of Order, if it be not thus with us.</p>
                  <p>And let all the Calamities and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of this preſent Life, be ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this Expectation; and improved likewiſe to ſtrengthen, and increaſe ſuch Deſires of a better State. This is one deſign of God in our Temporal Croſſes, to aſſiſt our Victory over this World, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97664:52"/>make us more intenſely and earneſtly to aſpire after Heaven; to teach us to long for everlaſting Reſt, and Peace, and Glory; to bring us practically to reckon, and conclude, that the expected Glory that is to be revealed in us, will infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out ballance all the ſufferings of our preſent State.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In ſhort,</hi> if you believe and expect ſuch a bleſſed Change, let the Apoſtles Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation take place, to <hi>be ſtedfaſt, unmovable, allways abounding in the work of the Lord, for you know it cannot be in vain in the Lord.</hi> Do not regret the Thoughts of labouring and ſuffering, for a little while more and longer in this Body; you need not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend you ſhall be looſers, or fear to have a hard Batgain: For your preſent Sorrows, and ſufferings, and difficult Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, can laſt but a little while, and ſhall have an eternal Recompence: If we are never ſo abundant in the Work of the Lord, if we begin never ſo ſoon, and laſt never ſo long, it ſhall not be in vain in the Lord, If therefore you thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and expect, be perſwaded to give all Diligence, adding to your Faith Vertue, to Vertue Knowledg to Knowledg Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to Temperance Patience, to Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence Godlineſs, to Godlineſs Brotherly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs, to Brotherly-kindneſs Charity,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97664:52"/>being filled with all the Fruits of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs that are by Chriſt Jeſus to the Glory and Praiſe of God, that an Entrance may be adminiſtred to you abundantly, into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Let us follow after, that we may apprehend that, for which alſo we are apprehended of Chriſt Jeſus. Let us reach forth unto thoſe things that are before, forgetting thoſe which are behind, and preſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Mark of the Prize of the high Calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus; that if by any means we might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto the Reſurrection of the dead.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.11, 12, 13.</note> Let us remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber we are to be but a little while in this Body, and this earthly Houſe is appointed for Labour, it is a work-houſe; <hi>Let us</hi> therefore <hi>give all Diligence to work out our Salvation,</hi> as knowing we ſhall not be long in the Body. This is the Apoſtles Argument as to himſelf, (and equally concerns us) 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12, 13.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:97664:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of the Characters of ſuch, who may, and ought to, long for this Glorious Change; who have a Title to the Deſired Bleſſedneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FIfthly,</hi> How ſollicitous ſhould we be to find in our ſelves the <hi>Characters</hi> of ſuch to whom theſe Deſires are ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and to clear up our <hi>Title</hi> to that bleſſed State, which the Followers of Chriſt do thus earneſtly long for? The Promiſe of the Heavenly Inheritance is annexed to our being <hi>born of God,</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born <hi>from above;</hi> You muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore look after the Renovation of the Divine Image and Life, by the Spirit of Life and Power in Jeſus Chriſt: that the Holy Spirit may Witneſs with your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to his own Work; that you may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and diſcern thoſe holy Affections as the Fruits of the Spirit, which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the Children of God; ſuch, as an humble Fear of him, and diligent
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97664:53"/>Care to pleaſe him; a fervent Love to God and Chriſt, an intire Reſignation to his Will; Holy Zeal for his Intereſt and Glory, and truſt in his Word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, till your Natures are changed by the Spirit of Chriſt, and you are ſo made meet for the Heavenly Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, you cannot have a ſhare in this Bleſſedneſs no more than if the legal Bar be not removed by the forgiveneſs of Sin, or your Perſons not reconciled by the Blood of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>The Qualification of the Heirs of this great Salvation is variouſly deſcribed in Scripture. Sometimes by <hi>Faith,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by <hi>Regeneration,</hi> ſometimes by <hi>Heavenly Affections,</hi> ſometimes by <hi>Holy O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,</hi> and <hi>Fruitfulneſs in Good Works:</hi> All muſt concur to ſuit us, and to Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle us to the Heavenly State.</p>
                  <p>You are therefore to inquire after the <hi>Characters</hi> of the Children of God, and the Heirs of Heaven, which is a ſtate of Sinleſs Perfection: And therefore to examine whether you are brought to loath your ſelves for your Sins, and that there is no ſin but you would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know, and are as deſirous to be rid of; and would rather be freed from Sin, than from Affliction: Whether you do not aſpire after the higheſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97664:54"/>of Holineſs? Whether you would not rather be perfect in the Love of God, and the Obedience of his Will, than have all the Riches and Pleaſures of the World? Whether you do not like, and love that Degree of Holineſs in others, that you have not yet attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your ſelves? Whether you do not love the Image of God and Chriſt, whereſoever you can diſcern it? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you do not endeavour to <hi>Mortifie the Fleſh,</hi> not to live or walk after it, but to be Crucified to the World, and with your chiefeſt care and endeavour, to ſerve and pleaſe God, and enjoy him for ever; depending on Chriſt his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and Interceſſion, and Spirit, for all your Grace and Glory; all your Hopes of Acceptance with God, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, or Title for Communion with him; giving up your ſelves intirely to be governed by him, being willing to obey his Law, whatſoever it ſhall coſt you; watching over your Heart, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and Thoughts, as well as out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Actions, taking Pleaſure in the Worſhip and Service of God, as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Work, reſigning to God, and being devoted to his Will, Praying fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently for his Grace, and caſting your ſelves on his Mercy, through Jeſus Chriſt for Eternal Life.</p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:97664:54"/>
                  <p> Theſe are ſome of the <hi>Characters</hi> of ſuch, as are <hi>Heirs of Salvation.</hi> Theſe you muſt look after; and then endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to advance, in a Joyful Hope and Aſſurance, that the Heavenly Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is yours; labouring for a ſetled Conſcience, growing in Grace, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in Mortified Affections to the World; and living in the Exerciſe of Grace, by careful obedience to God, as thoſe that are abſolutely devoted to him, and hope to live in his Bleſſed Preſence for ever.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:97664:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>How Few Christians live in the Exerciſe of ſuch Deſires after the Bleſſed Change. What may be the Reaſon. That ſome fear of Death, and particularly of a painful Death, may conſiſt with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs. That elder Chriſtians, and the Sickly and Infirm, ſhould endeavour to quicken ſuch a Deſire of Deliverance by Death. Reproof and Exhortation in reference hereto.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SIxthly.</hi> Let us be Aſhamed that we find in our ſelves no more of this holy frame. That we ſo over-love this Earthly Houſe, and are afraid of Death: <hi>That our Deſires are ſo faint toward this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Change.</hi> How ſhameful is our back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs and unwillingneſs to depart, and be with Chriſt? And how faulty are the Cauſes of it! which, in
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Mourner's Companion,</hi> Diſcourſe 3d. <hi>The Saints Deſire to be with Chriſt.</hi>
                     </note> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97664:55"/>Diſcourſe I have open'd. How is it that ſo few can ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Have we not Experienced enough of the Vanity and Vexation of this World, to make us willing of a better Abode? Have we not ſinned and ſuffered enough in this Body, to deſire to be uncloathed? at leaſt to wait patiently the Pleaſure of God for our Removal? And ſo glorious is the Change, which Chriſtians expect, that one would think there ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be need of <hi>Patience,</hi> to make a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever wait till then. But whatever the exerciſe of this Patience, under preſent Burdens may be, we need not doubt but one hours Enjoyment, will make amends for all our Waiting and Preparing.</p>
                  <p>It cannot be long with the <hi>Youngeſt</hi> of us. Let us not put it at a great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, for that will quench the Coal of Heavenly Deſire, if we look upon Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as Twenty or Thirty years off. We know not how ſoon God may call us; But have great Reaſon to lament the ſtrangeneſs of our Thoughts to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly State, and the faintneſs of our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, when the Promiſed Felicity is ſo attractive! Do we think we ſhall live ever the longer for being unwilling to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97664:56"/>Dye? Can it enter into our Thoughts, that our exceſſive Love of the Body will procure our Continuance in it?</p>
                  <p>Is it poſſible we ſhould imagine, that ſincerity of Love to Chriſt is conſiſtent with our Backwardneſs to go to him, and live with him? Why then do we not aſpire more earneſtly after this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Change? How is it that we groan under the Burdens of this Earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, and yet are loth to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</p>
                  <p>Will a Sick Man be afraid of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery? Or, a Priſoner tremble at the News of a Goal-delivery? No more ſhould a real Chriſtian be afraid of Death, or unwilling of it: For, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Death, and Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion, and Promiſe of Chriſt; it is to a Believer a quick Paſſage from Sickneſs to eternal Health, from Toil and Labour, Captivity and Sorrow, to everlaſting Reſt, and Liberty, and Joy.</p>
                  <p>I think, (<hi>ſays
<note n="*" place="bottom">Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> of <hi>Self-denial,</hi> p. 202.</note> one,</hi>) God has pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely cloathed your Soul with ſo poor a Dreſs, that you ſhould be the leſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97664:56"/>to be uncloathed; and might learn to ſet more by your Souls, than by your Bodies, and make more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Proviſion for them. It ſeems he has purpoſely lodged you in ſo poor a Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that you ſhould not be at too much Care for it, nor be too loth to leave it. You have its daily Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Infirmities and Pains, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of its Filth and Loathſomneſs, to tell you of its Meanneſs: And why ſhould you be ſo unwilling that ſo frail a Body ſhould be turned to Duſt? Duſt it is, and to Duſt it is Sentenced. When the Soul has left it but a Week, Men can ſcarce indure to ſee it, or ſmell it; And ſhould the breaking of ſuch an Earthen Veſſel be ſo unpleaſant a thing to you? And, for its <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs,</hi> though, ſo far as it is obedient, it was ſervicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your Souls and to God; Yet was it ſo refractory, ill-diſpoſed, and diſobedient, that it proved no better than your Enemy. Many a Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it hath entertained and cheriſhed, and many a Sin hath it drawn you to commit. Your Senſes have let in a World of Vanity, your Wandering Eyes have called in Covetouſneſs, and Pride, and Luſt. Your Greedy Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites have been ſo eager on the Bait,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97664:57"/>that they have too often born down your Faith and Reaſon, and drawn you to Exceſs in Meats or Drinks, for Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or Manner, for Quality, or Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, or both. Many a Groan theſe Sins have coſt you, and a ſad uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Life you have had by reaſon of them, in compariſon of what you might have had, and this Fleſh has been the Mother, or the Nurſe of all. You were engaged, by your <hi>Baptiſmal Covenant,</hi> to Fight againſt it, when you entered into the Church; and, if you are <hi>Christians,</hi> this Combate has been your daily Work, and much of the Buſineſs of your Lives; And yet are you loth to have the Victory, and ſee your Enemy under your feet? Have you fought your ſelves into Friendſhip with it, that you are ſo tender of it? Do you not know, that when you are the greateſt Friends to the Body, it will be the moſt dangerous Enemy to you? Do not think that it is only <hi>Sin,</hi> and not the <hi>Body,</hi> that is the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> which the Scripture calls your Enemy: For it is the Body, as inclining to Creatures, from which the ſinful Soul cannot reſtrain it: It is <hi>the Body,</hi> as having an inordinate ſenſitive Appetite, and Imagination, and ſo diſtempered, as that it rebels
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97664:57"/>againſt the Spirit, and caſteth off the Rule of Reaſon, and would not be cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of its Deſires, but have the Rule of all its ſelf. Was it not the very <hi>Fleſh</hi> it ſelf that <hi>Paul</hi> ſays he fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and kept under, and brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Subjection, leſt he ſhould be a Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.26. Why ſhould Sin be called Fleſh and Body, but that it is the Body, or Fleſh, that is the principal ſeat of thoſe ſins, that are ſo called? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How earneſtly ſhould we beg of God, that Faith and Hope in Vigorous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, that may kindle our Deſires, and Love towards the Heavenly State, and make us long to behold the Lord in Glory? when we ſhall put off this Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and our Souls be filled with Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Light and Love. Certainly, if we do not now deſire it, we ſhall never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it: For, we can never be happy by full ſatisfaction, in that which we do not know enough of, to make us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: But the little Knowledge and Love of God, which a real Chriſtian now hath, muſt needs make him Importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in his Requeſts for more, and will make him value his Hopes of a better State, beyond all the Pleaſures of Sin, and all the Poſſeſſions of this World.</p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:97664:58"/>
                  <p> O How Paſſionately have ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Perſons lamented the weakneſs of their Deſires and Love, and cryed out for more of Heavenly Life and Light, and Love to God! <q>O
<note n="*" place="bottom">Mr. <hi>Baxter's Dying Thoughts,</hi> p. 184. 212.</note> where is the longing, the rejoycing, the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing Faith? VVhere is the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant familiarity above, that ſhould make a Thought of Chriſt and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to be ſweeter to me, than the Thought of Friends, and Health, or all the Pleaſure, and Proſperity in the World? Do thoſe that dwell in God, and God in them, and have their Heart and Converſation in Heaven, attain to no more clear and ſatisfying Precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that bleſſed State, than I have yet attained? Is there no more Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance above to be here expected? No livelier ſenſe of future Joys? No ſweeter Fore taſtes? No fuller ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Doubts and Fears? Alas! How many Chriſtians are leſs afraid to go to a Priſon, than to their God; and had rather be Paniſhed to a Land of Strangers, than ſent to Heaven? <hi>O
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97664:58"/>Lord,</hi> muſt I, that am called thy Child, and an Heir of Heaven, and a <hi>Co heir with Chriſt,</hi> have no more Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with my Glorified Lord, and no more Love to thee, who art my Portion, before I go hence and come to thee? — Muſt I go hence, ſo like a Stranger, to my home? O what do I beg for ſo frequently, and ſo earneſtly, for the ſake of my Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as the Spirit of Life and Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that may ſhew me the pleaſed face of God, and unite all my Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to my glorified Head, and draw up this dark, and drowſie Soul, to love and long to be with thee?</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>O God forbid, that this ſinful Fleſh ſhould be more powerful to draw me downward, than Faith, and Hope, and Love, to carry my Deſires up to God. O thou that freely gaveſt me thy Grace, maintain it to the laſt againſt its Enemies, and make it finally Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious: It came from thee, it hath been preſerved by thee, it is on thy ſide, and wholly for thee; O let it not now fail, and be conquer'd by blind and baſe Carnality, or by the Temptations of a Helliſh conquered Enemy! — It is thine Image which thou loveſt, it is a Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97664:59"/>and Heavenly Beam; VVhat will a Soul be without it, but a Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of Darkneſs, a Devil for Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and dead to Holineſs and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? — O rather deny me the Light of the Sun, than the Light of thy Countenance: Leſs miſerable had I been without Light or Being, than without thy Grace.— O forſake not a Sinner in his extremity, who conſents to thy Covenant, and would not forſake thee. My God, I have often ſinned againſt thee, but yet thou knoweſt, I would fain be thine. I have not ſerved thee with that Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, Fidelity and Delight, as ſuch a Maſter ſhould have been ſerved; But yet I would not forſake thy Service, nor change my Maſter, or my Work. I can ſay with thy Servant <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. 27.23. That <hi>thou art the God whoſe I am, and whom I ſerve.</hi> And O that I could ſerve thee better! For to ſerve thee, is but to receive thy Grace, and uſe it for my own, and others good; and ſo to glorifie thee, and pleaſe thy Will, which being Love it ſelf, it pleaſed beſt, when we receive it, and do moſt good.— Nothing in this World is more my Grief, than that I love thee no more: Forſake not then a Sinner, that would
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:97664:59"/>not forſake thee, that looks towards thee, that feels it, as his trouble, to be ſo dark and ſtrange unto thee; that groaneth, and gaſpeth after thee, feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to his greateſt ſorrow, that while he is preſent in the Body, he is abſent from the Lord. <hi>My Lord,</hi> I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do in this World, but to ſeek and ſerve thee. — O pardon all my Carnal Thoughts, and all my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful Neglects, of thy precious Grace and Love; and let the fuller Communications of thy forfeited Grace, now tell me by experience; that thou doſt forgive me.— When I have ſaid, VVill the Lord caſt off for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? And will he be favourable no more? My Conſcience has replyed, That <hi>this is mine Infirmity</hi> I never wanted Comfort, becauſe thou ever wantedſt Mercy; but becauſe I wanted Faith, and Fitneſs to receive it, and perceive it; But haſt thou not Mercy alſo to give me, even that Fitneſs, and that Faith? <hi>My God,</hi> all is of thee, and through thee, and all is to thee: and when I have the Felicity, the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of all for ever will be thine; If I can live and dye in truſting in thee, ſurely I ſhall not be confounded.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:97664:60"/>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">See a more full Example of the Acting of <hi>Holy Deſires</hi> towards the Bleſſed Change, in the Cloſe of his <hi>Saints Everlasting Reſt.</hi>
                     </note> Theſe be ſome of the <hi>Dying Thoughts</hi> of that Excellent Perſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>And yet, my Friends, miſtake me not. I ſay not that all are Graceleſs, that are afraid of Death. For Nature deſires Life, even under Sufferings that are but tolerable, rather than dye: And this is from meer natural, neceſſary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, which Free-will hath not full Power againſt. Death, as the Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our frame, as the Separation of Soul and Body, cannot, for it ſelf, be loved: The putrifying of this Body in the Grave, the greatneſs of the Change of Death, the darkneſs of our Minds, and the weakneſs of our Grace, the remaining Senſe of Sin, with the dreadful Majeſty of that God before whom we muſt appear, joined with our Natural Averſeneſs to Dye, may make us ſhrink and tremble; But the Faith of the Inviſible VVorld, the Love of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97664:60"/>God and Chriſt, and a deſire to enjoy him, and pleaſe him, and be with him, ſhould do much to overcome theſe Fears, and make us willing.</p>
                  <p>Though ſome remaining <hi>Fear</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs,</hi> yet remember, that not to deſire and long for this Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed State, though mix'd with a Fear of intervening Death, is highly criminal and faulty: For the Love of God and Chriſt, and earneſt Deſires to be like him, and to be with him, ſeems to be the better half of all Religion, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 13. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. Not to deſire this Bleſſed Change, is directly a ſin againſt the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2 12 1 Pet. 1.12.</note> 
                     <hi>called to the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Glory of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> VVithout ſuch Deſires, we comply not with the Deſign and VVill of God, who <hi>hath called us to his eternal Glory by Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> For how can his Call be anſwered, without an Inclination of Heart to ſuch a State, and a Deſire after it?</p>
                  <p>For a real Member of Chriſt, and Heir of Heaven, to be only <hi>Content</hi> to ſee the Lord, to be <hi>Content</hi> to be for ever in his Bleſſed Preſence, and perfectly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and freed from Sin, is a very hard and harſh expreſſion. Men are cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:97664:61"/>eager and ambitious after earthly good; And ſhall a Chriſtian's Deſire be leſs earneſt after the Heavenly Glory?</p>
                  <p>I grant, ſome remaining Fear of Death may conſiſt with Integrity; when it is not God and Heaven we are averſe to, but Death that ſtands in the way; or when it is becauſe of our Doubts of God's Acceptance of us. For I queſtion not but moſt upright Chriſtians would rather dye than live, might they but hope to be with Chriſt, and enjoy the Divine Preſence. As others would be glad of a Removal, might it be <hi>without Dying,</hi> becauſe they fear the Pains and Terrors of a dying Hour. Might they not be uncloathed, but cloathed upon by an immediate Tranſlation, they care not how ſoon it were. For there be many ſuch, who deſire the Second Coming of Chriſt unfeignedly, and the Bleſſed Conſequences of it, to whom all the parts of the Heavenly State and Life are ſweet and grateful, who live and walk in their Integrity before God, though their Grace prevail not againſt this Fear of death.</p>
                  <p>VVhereas you ought to conſider, that the Throes and Pangs of Travelling VVomen, in ordinary caſes, may be ſuppoſed to equal, or exceed the Pains
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97664:61"/>of Death. (And who knows the divine Supports that may make our Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion eaſie?) yet many a Mother has Courage and Patience, by the Hopes of Life, and of a living Child, when all theſe Sorrows ſhall be ſoon forgotten.</p>
                  <p>And ſhall the Knowledge and Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Heaven, and Eternal Life be leſs powerful, to influence thy Soul againſt the Fear of Death? How many have been inabled to conquer the Fear of Death, and been diſpleaſed with their Friends, that talked of their Recovery as hopeful, and have told them, that ſuch Diſcourſe was not pleaſing, they had rather dye, and be with Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Is it thy Uſefullneſs to Relations and Friends, or to the Intereſt of Chriſt in this World, that makes thee unwilling? Think a little, Are you fitter to Judge and determine of that than he? Can he not do his own Work without thee? Conſider therefore, Chriſtians, you that know you cannot have an Houſe above without pulling down this earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacle; you that know you cannot get to Heaven but by dying, and pretend to be related to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Country: Are you deſirous of nothing better than the Fruits of this Earth? What a contempt of God and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97664:62"/>Chriſt, What a gratification of the Devil, what a contradiction to your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and hope, does this Backwardneſs carry with it? yea a contradiction to the very End and Deſign of <hi>all Religion;</hi> which is a dead, and vain, infignificant, and trifling thing, if it refer not to <hi>a bleſſed Eternity</hi> beyond the Grave, and if it bring us not to deſire, and chuſe it as our End.</p>
                  <p>You eſpecially who are <hi>Old Diſciples,</hi> and have been long in the School of Chriſt, ſhould conſider this. You know you muſt ere long lay down this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle and be uncloathed, you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to hope ſhortly to enter into the World of Joy; What a ſhame is it, that your Sight is no clearer, your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception no quicker, your Apprehenſions no higher, your Deſires no ſtronger, as to this expected Bleſſedneſs after Death! though you are ſenſible you draw nearer to the things believed, and hoped for, and that within a little while you expect the Promiſes will have a full Performance as to <hi>you;</hi> that you are almoſt <hi>there,</hi> where Faith ſhall paſs into Sight and Love; You are almoſt ready to take your place in Glory, where Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions are gone before you; O how is it, that you are no more Joyfully
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:97664:62"/>affected with theſe Hopes: How is it, that your Thoughts are ſo doubtful, your Deſires ſo ſluggiſh? That this Body, and this preſent World, is ſo unduely loved? even though the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſenſible things be almoſt gone; though bodily Infirmities and Pains, make this preſent Dwelling uneaſie: For they require your Patience, and call aloud to you to haſten your work, to ſet looſe, and prepare to come away. God hath made you weary of this World, and makes you often cry for divine Aſſiſtance and Grace: He hath given you to know by experience, that He alone muſt be the Portion of your Souls, his Favour alone your Life, and Heaven or nothing your happineſs: You find that the Hope of Heaven is your only Comfort: For ſuch as <hi>you,</hi> to be unwilling to dye, who, by Age and Weakneſs, have one ſoot in Heaven already, is moſt inexcuſable.</p>
                  <p>You have found that your Souls are uſually worſt, when your Bodys have been beſt, and when the Body is in the beſt State, it is uſually worſt with the Soul: ſhould it not therefore be your care, when the outward Man is decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the inward Man ſhould be aſpiring after God, and grow better?
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:97664:63"/>Has this vile and corruptible Fleſh been ſo much your Friend, that you are loth to be uncloathed? What Entertainment have you had in this World, that you ſhould be ſo loth to leave it? Have your Fears, and Cares, and Sorrows, by reaſon of the Body, been ſo delightful, that you would not that they ſhould have an end, that you do not groan to be cloathed upon with an Houſe from Heaven? Methinks, as every Pain and Ache, and Trouble, and Sickneſs, ſhould mind the wicked of their eternal Sorrows; ſo the bodily Infirmities, Decays, and Sickneſs of good Men, ſhould raiſe their Deſire to be with Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>O What a ſhame is it, as to All of us, that we no more deſire and groan to be delivered, when there is ſo glorious and bleſſed a State in view before us? That the Thoughts of theſe things are ſo cold and ſeldom! Our heavenly Affections ſo low and weak! What can be the reaſon? but that we look upon the heavenly Glory as at the diſtance of many Years to come, if at all we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and expect it? But this is <hi>ſhameful,</hi> to thoſe that profeſs by Death to expect a freedom from all the incumberances of Fleſh and Blood, of bodily Paſſions
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:97664:63"/>and Appetites, and of all the preſent Temptations of ſenſuality: who expect that our Time of Sinning and Suffering ſhall ſhortly end together, when we ſhall be releaſed from all the ſad Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of Mortality, and this vile and corruptible Body be raiſed in Glory. <hi>Shameful</hi> indeed for us, who believe a bleſſed State ſo near, when there ſhall be nothing from within, nor from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ever more to intercept, hinder, or abate our compleat Felicity: who look for the Light of Gods eternal Favour to ſhine upon us, and the plentiful plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Streams of eternal Goodneſs, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from God and the Lamb, to make our delight, and Joy perfect and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. And yet we do not, as we ought, deſire and long to be Partakers of this bleſſed State.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:97664:64"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Our Holy Friends Departed obtain their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires by Dying: this ſhould moderate our funeral Sorrows. A ſhort Account of the Exemplary Character of Mrs.</hi> Mary <hi>Doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, with ſome Paſſages of her laſt Sickneſs. The Concluſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſtly,</hi> HOW ſhould all this mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate our Sorrow, for the death of our holy Friends and Relations? whoſe earthly Houſe is pulled down, to enjoy a Heavenly one; Who groaned, and wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and longed, for that Diſolution, which we unduely Mourn for. Who are pleaſed with that Tranſlation, and Removal. which we bewail. It is but what they deſired, and long have wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for. They are now pleaſed, in the Happy Change of their old Earthly, Dwelling, for a Building of God, not made with Hands, eternal in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens. They are uncloathed to be Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon. Let us not then mourn for their Advancement to that Happy State, which they earneſtly aſpired after;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:97664:64"/>and which we our ſelves ſhould live in the Joyful Expectation of. Let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce rather, that they have finiſhed their Courſe; that their Souls are gone to Chriſt; That their Bodys ſhall reſt in their Graves for a Time, and hereafter ariſe in Glory. Let us think where our deceaſed holy Friends now are, what they See, and know, and do, and enjoy: what the State, and Life, and Company, and Employment above is: and how much better it is with them now, than when they were with us on Earth. They have received <hi>the End of their Faith and Hope,</hi> and ſo attained their deſire in the preſent <hi>Salvation of their Souls;</hi> and they have Aſſurance too as to their Bodies, That hereafter they ſhall be raiſed, and changed, and made like the glorious Body of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>Let us thus think in particular of our Good Friend <hi>Mrs. Doolittle,</hi> who hath put off this Earthly Tabernacle, and is entered into the glorious Aſſembly of the Friends af Chriſt above. What I ſhall ſay <hi>of her,</hi> is not meerly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with Cuſtom, concerning the Dead,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:97664:65"/>but in hopes to edifie and Inſtruct the Living.</p>
                  <p>I Know there be ſome, who diſguſt the publiſhing of any particular Paſſages of our departed Friends, how Imitable an Praile worthy ſoever: But it is the Fluttery and Falſhood often uſed on ſuch. Occaſions, concerning thoſe whoſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter will not bear a Commendation, that is the Cauſe. But I fear no ſuch Cenſube as to what I ſhall now ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming <hi>Her,</hi> whoſe Death and Funeral brings me <hi>here,</hi> and gives another Place this day to <hi>my Reverend Brother,</hi> than <hi>this,</hi> where he is wont to be.</p>
                  <p>God will not be diſpleaſed, that we ſhould Honour thoſe, whom he hath Honoured with eminent Grace. The Memory of the Righteous ſhall be bleſſed. And how ſhall others be perſwaded to follow the moſt Laudable Patterns, if we conceal particulars? At leaſt the Surviv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Relations, Friends, and Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance may be edified, and aſſiſted by it, in their Duty upon ſuch Providences. And I have the leſs to apprehend of Cavil, or Objection in the preſent Caſe, becauſe what I ſhall mention is from ſuch Hands as there can be no Doubt of the <hi>Truth,</hi> of what I ſhall ſay: and very many of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:97664:65"/>you here, will readily yield a concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Teſtimony.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>It ſhall be under three Heads. <hi>Firſt</hi> her perſonal Piety, or her general Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter as a Chriſtian. <hi>Secondly,</hi> her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Religion, or concerning her in the ſeveral Relations wherein ſhe ſtood, as faithfully diſcharging the Duties of them. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Her Chriſtian Deportment under bodily Infirmities and Sickneſs, with <hi>ſome more remarkable Paſſages in this her laſt Sickneſs,</hi> before ſhe put off this earthly Tabernacle.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> as to her <hi>Perſonal, Piety,</hi> and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Character as <hi>a Chriſtian,</hi> That ſhe was truly Serious and Religious in her <hi>Youth,</hi> and ſo eſteemed and judged abone forty years agoe, was the ground of her being choſen by her Husband, as the Companion of his Life. And God continued her to him in much Mercy, for about <hi>nine and thirty years:</hi> being pleaſed by her to build up his Houſe to ſuch a Degree, as not many Inſtances in City or Country can be given of the like. That out of his own Family, there was not one Solemn Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:97664:66"/>in <hi>Thirty nine</hi> or <hi>forty years;</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of two Children in the Month; and one newly wean'd; and none at all in the ſpace of <hi>five and twenty</hi> years. Let God have the Glory, and let Thankfulneſs to heaven be mixed with your mourning by this Reflection. I have many witneſſes amongſt you, who were acquainted with <hi>her ſerious Piety;</hi> and they who knew her beſt, had abundant proof of her ſecret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with God, and dayly retirement for Meditation and Prayer: and this very often early in the Morning. Which is Imitable by all of us, and one of the beſt Evidences of Unfeigned, Real, Living Religion, in the Power of it.</p>
                  <p>I do not underſtand, (and I like it not the worſe) that ſhe pretended to high flights of Confidence and Aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which few attain or preſerve very long: and I fear many deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by ſomewhat that is not of God under that Name. Yet when ſhe had any Darkneſs as to her Spiritual State, when ſhe was ſenſible of the weakneſs of her <hi>Love to Chriſt,</hi> and Lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; <hi>He</hi> who on all accounts was fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to aſſiſt her, endeavoured to let her know the Truth of that Grace, by diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:97664:66"/>of a threefold Love to Chriſt <hi>a Delighting Love, a Deſiring Love,</hi> and <hi>a Mourning Love:</hi> telling her that tho ſhe had not the <hi>former</hi> of theſe, to her Comfort: ſhe could not deny or diſown <hi>the two latter.</hi> And this helped to give her Satisfaction, and ſupport, concerning the Tryal of her State. She added Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly the Night before ſhe died, <hi>I look to Sincerity, and uprightneſs of Heart, as a ground of Comfort, but I do not put them in the room of Chriſt my only Saviour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Several years agoe ſhe read much in the practical Writings of <hi>Mr. Iſaac Ambroſe,</hi> particularly concerning <hi>Eternity,</hi> which made a very great Impreſſion on her Mind, ſo as that ſhe trembled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Apprehenſion, leſt ſhe ſhould come ſhort of that <hi>Bleſſed Eternity,</hi> there deſcribed. However under her Doubts and Fears, when <hi>the free Grace of God in Chriſt</hi> was diſcourſed of, ſhe could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably ſay, <hi>why then may not ſuch a one as I, be accepted by free Grace in Chriſt? and hope to be capable of Bleſſedneſs in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as well as others? this is a Faithful Saying, worthy of all acceptation,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt came into the World to ſave Sinners, of whom I am Chief.</hi> This ſhe did, and could ſay
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:97664:67"/>from her very Soul, and appeal therein to the Omniſcient Searcher of Hearts, and this was her Encouragement and Joy, that ſhe could Say it, <hi>I have reſigned my ſelf to God in Covenant again and again. I Bleſs the Lord who hath enabled me to devote, and give up my ſelf to be his. Lord? I am thine, Accept and Save me.</hi> And at another Time ſhe was able to ſay, <hi>I have had that Converſe with God, and Communion with him, that I would not part with for the whole World.</hi> This is more than many who are Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere attain unto. For tho ſome real Chriſtians have great Refreſhments, and ſupport, by Communication of Light, and Strength, and Joy upon a ſick and Death Bed: as if the Light of Glory ſhined into them, and they had the beginning of Heaven here; yet many others may want this, when they come to die, and Experience little of theſe exuberant Joys, through their whole Courſe. For God exerciſes <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> in the Diſpenſation of <hi>his</hi> Comforts, at that, and at other Times. Therefore the Judgment we ſhould make of Perſons, muſt rather be grounded on their general Courſe of Life, than on their particular frame in Sickneſs, or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the approach of Death; Some times by reaſon of the diſorder of the Blood
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97664:67"/>and Spirits, the Holieſt ſervants of God may be either Lumpiſh and Melancholy; or elſe Feveriſh and Phrenetcal: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times through the Temptations of the Devil, they may be unſetled in their Minds, or through Diſſertion ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortably to thoſe about them. They may afflict themſelves with diſpairing Thoughts, and leave the World under inward Darkneſs. Their agonies in death may be without any ſence of Comfort, and yet they may be accepted with God, and paſs to eternal Glory: becauſe we ſhall not be Judged according to that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Iuſtant of Death, but according to the general Courſe of our Life. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is obſerved in moſt caſes, that God does ſpeak peace to upright Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, before he takes them to himſelf. And thus it was with our <hi>Deceaſed briend,</hi> of which more preſently. But.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us Conſider her Carriage in each <hi>Relation.</hi> There were many things Im table in her Example, as a Wife, a Mother, a Miſtreſs, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Her <hi>Affection</hi> and <hi>Reverence</hi> to her <hi>Husband,</hi> were very obſervable. When he, among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of the faithful Servants of Chriſt,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:97664:68"/>was Silenced, and forbidden to Preach; though ſhe had then Children, and like to have more, and a conſiderable Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance was thereby to be ſtopped, and a growing Family to be caſt upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God; and many urged her to perſwade him to comply with the Impoſed Terms; ſhe wholly declin'd it, and would rather truſt God in a Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing State; leaving him intirely to his Conſcience, as the fitteſt Judge of his Obligations, Truſt, and Duty, in that Caſe.</p>
                  <p>When afterwards, of Conſequents to his Nonconformity, he met with any Difficulties, by continuing to Preach, ſhe patiently ſubmitted, and took joyfully the ſpoiling of their Goods; ſaying of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, when his Perſon was in hazard, That ſhe was ready, rather to adventure her own Life, then that his ſhould be in danger: as apprehending his to be more valuable to the World, and the Intereſt of Souls, than hers, or Twenty ſuch.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Affection</hi> ſhe continued all her Life, adviſing her Children in her laſt Sickneſs, to be careful of their Father, and tender of him <hi>in her Abſence:</hi> for by ſo mild, and good a word, ſhe ſpake of her
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:97664:68"/>
                     <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> then in proſpect. Adviſing them withal to Love one another, and be kindly affectioned to each other: Praying particularly for her Son, whom ſhe had the Comfort to ſee ſetled in the Sacred Work of the Miniſtry, that God would furniſh him with ſuitable Strength of Body and Spirit, and crown his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry with an abundant Bleſſing.</p>
                  <p>Not long before ſhe died, ſhe thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully owned the Goodneſs of God to her, in the Spiritual Aſſiſtance and Comfort, ſhe received by <hi>ſuch Relations,</hi> who had an Intereſt in Heaven, and could plead it for her in Prayer, while ſhe was lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing on a Sick Bed. <hi>O what a Mercy is it,</hi> (ſaid ſhe, when her Husband and Son had both been Praying for her, with great Fervency and inlargedneſs of Heart,) <hi>What a Mercy is it, that I ſhould have ſuch Relations, to plead with God for me.</hi> And, at laſt, when ſhe took her Farewel of her Husband, <hi>ſhe thanked him for all his Love, and all his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> as audibly as ſhe was then able to ſpeak.</p>
                  <p>Many Memorable things ſhe ſaid, by way of Counſel and Advice, to her Children. As concerning <hi>the Deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:97664:69"/>of the Heart,</hi> and the need of ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it again and again; for God knows it, and will not be mocked. Exhorting them to ſeek God with their whole Heart, to Pray fervently, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately for his Grace and Favour, and not in a ſlight and overly manner, as if they were indifferent whether God did Anſwer, or Deny. I hope they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it, and act accordingly.</p>
                  <p>At another time, in her Sickneſs, ſhe cried out, whilſt her Children were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her, <hi>O Love the Lord all ye his Saints! Love the Lord ye my Children! Love him, Fear him!</hi> She deſired that <hi>they</hi> would Pray for her, and ſhe aſſigned a good Reaſon why they ſhould; <hi>For,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>I have often Prayed to God for you, when you could not Pray for your ſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Under this Head, I might add ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of her Carriage even to <hi>Servants,</hi> to whom ſhe gave the moſt Seaſonable Counſel, particularly in her laſt Sickneſs, to the Servant that attended her, to be much in Reading the Holy Scriptures, to value Catechiſing, and be diligent in learning the Principles of Religion, to be faithful in her Place, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But this leads me,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:97664:69"/>
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To the Laſt Scene of her Life, to ſpeak of her deportment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Bodily Weakneſs and Pains; under which her Patience and Submiſſion were very becoming, and truly Chriſtian. VVhen a day or two before ſhe died, her Relations ſeemed more than uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned; She asked them why they were ſo; ſaying, <hi>It is not Death yet; I may out-live this, and be buffeted by Sathan, as a Roaring Lion, before I die.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When ſhe could not ſleep in the Night, ſhe ſaid the next Morning, <hi>I thought this would have been a Comfortable night to me:</hi> but preſently recollected her ſelf, ſaying, <hi>So it is, for it is a Mercy I am out of Hell, when Ten thouſands are caſt into the bottomleſs pit, that never ſinned as I have done.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How well ſhe bore her own <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> and how little ſollicitous ſhe was about the Iſſue of it, is evident from her own words; <hi>O how comfortable is Death, when ſin is Pardoned, and God Reconciled? O that
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:97664:70"/>I might entertain kind, and good Thoughts of God, and truſt him, though he ſlay me.</hi> When ſpoken to about her Recovery; She could ſay, <hi>I do not hope it; and bleſſed be God I do not deſire it.</hi> When asked, Are you not in a ſtreight about it? Are you willing to leave Husband, and Children, and all to be with Chriſt? She declared <hi>her Willingneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is true, ſometime; ſhe complained, that ſhe had not ſuch vigorous, lively, melting Affections, in Sickneſs, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time formerly in Health: yet ſhe depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on God ſtill.</p>
                  <p>VVhen ſhe was Asked, VVhether ſhe kept her Thoughts employed about <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi> She Anſwered, <hi>I do what I can.</hi> And the Night before ſhe died, after a little ſilence, when ſhe was queſtioned concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her <hi>Thoughts,</hi> VVhat ſhe was think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of? She Anſwered <hi>Three things,</hi> (which are fit for all of us often to think of) <hi>a Deceitful Heart, a Painful Death, and a Tempting Devil:</hi> God reſtrained the <hi>laſt,</hi> and carried her above the Fear, and Feeling of the <hi>Second:</hi> for though ſhe ſaid, <hi>She feared a hard Death,</hi> as many Holy Perſons do. Yet ſhe added, <hi>I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:97664:70"/>to the will of God, he will not lay upon me more than he will enable me to bear.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>VVhen the 17th Chapter of <hi>John</hi> was Read to her, where are thoſe remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conſolatory words of Chriſt, <hi>Father, I will, that thoſe whom thou haſt given me, may be with me, to behold my Glory;</hi> though ſhe could hardly ſpeak, ſo as to be heard, ſhe made a ſhift to ſay, <hi>O Excellent, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent;</hi> expreſſing her <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> and <hi>Joy,</hi> as far as her weakneſs would permit.</p>
                  <p>Her <hi>Humility,</hi> and <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſpicuous during this Sickneſs. <hi>O what a Mercy is it,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>that ſuch a one as I ſhould have Hopes of Heaven, of the Pardon of Sin, and of an Intereſt in Chriſt?</hi> And yet when any of thoſe holy expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſhe uſed were repeated in Praver to God, by thoſe who aſſiſted her, She deſired, no ſuch Speeches of hers ſhould be mentioned to God; <hi>For,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>my Frame is not equal, and alike a way. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think, and ſpeak the ſame things, at one time that I do at another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An hour or two before ſhe left this World, ſhe teſtified her deſire to be with Chriſt; ſaying, <hi>How long! O Lord, how
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:97664:71"/>long! (if my Work be done) Come and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me!</hi> She begged they would pray for her, that her Strength might hold out to the laſt; that God would not leave her, nor hide his Face in the Agonies of Death. She defired rather to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, than to continue in the Body: ſaying, <hi>I Look, I Long, I Hope; O when will the hour come? Muſt I tarry, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure another Night! Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly! Haſt thou no Bowels for me? Whilſt thou wert on Earth, thou wert full of Compaſſion to poor Sinners, and art thou not the ſame in Heaven?</hi> After this, ſhe own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf refreſhed by Prayer, and that though her Body was weak, her Heart was in a good Frame; being much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruited, and encouraged by Prayer. And ſo ſhe commended her foul to God, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on him to the very laſt, for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Aſſiſtance, and Succour, through the dark Valley, and to accept and receive her departing Soul; and ſo <hi>ſhe died in the Lord,</hi> and <hi>ſlept in Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God grant to us, as he did to her, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Help in that hour of Darkneſs and Trouble; and enable us to follow the Exemplary Faith and Patience, of thoſe who are gone before; that with them at laſt, we may receive the end of our
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:97664:71"/>Faith and Hope, the Salvation of our Souls, and the Reſurrection of our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in the day of Chriſt, who is the Reſurrection and the Life; in whom, whoſoever believes, ſhall never die the Second Death; but the Spirit, that raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſt from the Dead, ſhall quicken our Mortal Bodies, and make them like to his moſt glorious Body, that with Soul and Body we may be for ever with the Lord. <hi>To him be Glory for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:97664:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books to be Sold by</hi> A. Chandler, <hi>of the ſame Author.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe <hi>Mourners Companion,</hi> or <hi>Funeral Diſcourſes</hi> on Several Texts.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Exhortation to Repentance, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> among <hi>Protestants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Preſent Correction</hi> and <hi>Reproof of Sin;</hi> or a Diſcourſe on 2 <hi>Jer.</hi> 19. <hi>Thine own Iniquities ſhall Correct thee, and thy Backſlidings ſhall Reprove thee.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>A <hi>Sermon</hi> of St. <hi>Peter's</hi> Sin, and True Repentance. Printed for <hi>S. Wade,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> under the <hi>Piaza</hi> of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
